<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The famous historie of Albions queene VVherein is discoursed King Edwards ielosie, Queene Katherines chastetie, the Duke of Suffolkes loyaltie, and the Barron of Buckinghams treacherie.</title>
            <author>R. G., fl. 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01382)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 343:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The famous historie of Albions queene VVherein is discoursed King Edwards ielosie, Queene Katherines chastetie, the Duke of Suffolkes loyaltie, and the Barron of Buckinghams treacherie.</title>
                  <author>R. G., fl. 1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VV. VVhite for T. Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Corne-hill neare to the Exchange at the signe of the Catte and Parrettes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: R.G.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:1"/>
            <p>THE Famous Hiſtorie of Albions Queene.</p>
            <p>VVherein is diſcourſed King Edwards Ielo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Queene Katherines chaſtetie, the Duke of Suffolkes loyaltie, and the Barron of Buckinghams treacherie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by VV. VVhite for T. PAVIER, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Corne-hill neare to the Exchange at the ſigne of the Catte and Parrettes. 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL EDMVND MVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LINEVX ESQVIER, health, happineſſe, and proſperitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall report (right Worſhipfull) of your gallant minde and noble diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, hath imboldned me to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> this my worthleſſe labour to the view of your ingenious iudgement: and the long deſiers of my willing minde being now ſet on fier with the fame of your bright renowne, preſageth my m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes good fortune; which although it be but barren, yet wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the deaw of your gratious acceptance, will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be more fruitfull. What the Storie is, let your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome conceite: my Subiect is, <hi>The Vertues of a chaſt Queene, and the loyaltie of a faythfull Subiect; the triumphes of an honorable minde, ſhrowded vnder the habite of a ielous King.</hi> Accept it (ſweete M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tialiſt) with a fauourable countenance, and my hopes are aduanced. After the thundering alarums of dreadfull Warre, Souldiers will ſometime recreate themſelues with pleaſant diſcourſes: be you then, I beſeech you (right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) a kind Patron to an vnworthy witt, that I may ſay vnto my muſe, Happy is thy chaunce, and fortunate thy proceedinges.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By your diuoted and humble welwiller till death.</hi> R. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:3"/>
            <head>THE Famous Hiſtorie of ALBIONS QVEENE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 1.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> How King Edward grew ielous of Queene Katherine, through the flatterie of the Barron of Buckingham.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout three hundred yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the royall name of great <hi>Plantaginet</hi> poſſeſſed the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Diadem of this Mayden Land: in which golden age, there raigned as then one <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Senior,</hi> a Prince of moſt excellent wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: but yet in the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce of his gouernment, croſt with many ſtrange cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities through diſloyall actions of falſe ſubiectes.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Edward</hi> was not any of thoſe royall <hi>Edwardes,</hi> which liued ſince the <hi>Normayne</hi> Conquerour made <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> happy by his lawful clayme, but one linially deſcended from the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperors, who in the ſpring time of his blooming youth, tooke to wife a moſt wiſe and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene, beautified with many ſingular good guiftes of nature and princely qualeties, beſeeming ſo worthy a
<pb facs="tcp:6036:4"/>Lady: which Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> (for ſo was ſhe called) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather imployed a dutifull care to adorne and ſet foorth her huſbands Princely houſe and Scepter, with ſurpaſſing glorie and rich renowne of vertue: and beſides that, ſhe ſo worthely defended her owne honour againſt a number of looſe Loueres, which dayly practiſed the conqueſt of her chaſtetie.</p>
               <p>But now her betrothed huſband King <hi>Edward,</hi> being troubled diuers wayes with the hurly burlies of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nothing at all ſolaced his minde in the company of his vertuous Queene, by which he grew in miſtruſt of her chaſtety, greatly fearing leaſt others ſhould loue that, which himſelfe liked: or that ſhe fauoured that, which he falſely ſuſpected, his telous minde neuer reſted ſatisfied: partly of himſelfe led with fond beliefe, but chiefly incenſed through the faythles falſehood of one <hi>George de Combria,</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Barron of Buckingam,</hi> being aduaunced from low and poore parentage to the kings Court, and not onely made one of his priuie counſell, but placed in all digneties next vnto his perſon.</p>
               <p>This proude Barron, enuying the honour of Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> cloſely ſtuffed the Kings conſeated head with falſe reportes, and as it were coniured the ſperit of I cloſie into his minde, againſt the good and gratious Princeſſe: which vniuſt occations of griefe being ſetled, &amp; vnkindnes ſo deepely graued in his hart, that neuer after it could be raced out by any meanes whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> being thus ſuncke into the bottome of diſpayre, fetched many greeuous ſighes, and often in great ſorrow of hart would breath foorth this, or ſuch like lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
               <p>Oh my vntruſty Wife and Lady! wherefore haſt thou wounded thus my hidden loue, and inforced me to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne
<pb facs="tcp:6036:4"/>of thy trecherous infidelitie? Thou haſt ingaged my honour, diſcharged my perſon from renowne, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed diſhonour to my Scepter. Oh! I launce foorth into the gulfe of dolorous diſtreſſe. My marſhall ſtaffe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe is broken in peeces, and I am ledde into voluntarie ſeruitude, deceitfully bereft from the freedome of my nuptiall life, and ſacrefized a ſlaue into the handes of tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous varlets.</p>
               <p>In this manner many a day King <hi>Edward</hi> fed his ielous minde with vaine immaginations, caſting him ſelfe from the lofty mountaine of paſſed ioyes, into the bottomeleſſe pit of preſent woe. So on the other ſide, the Barron of <hi>Buckingam,</hi> being hardoned in ſhameleſſe audacities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred him with a new onſet, to dyet his ſmell with a quicker ſcent: and ſo eſpying a time to play with the ſword of ſedition, he in preſence of many of King <hi>Edwardes</hi> Lords, vomited out this wrongfull accuſation that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>If proteſting of loyall duetie to your worthy Maieſtie, or floods of inceſſant teares diſtilling from the cundets of my ſorrowfull eyes, may make perfect ſhew of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes honeſt minde, as yet neuer blemiſhed with the breach of diſhoneſtie, or euer touched or found guyltie of trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous crime: in regard of which true obedience (moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Prince) accompt my ſpeaches for a veritie, and nearely looke into the wronges of your Marriage bedde, which ignorance hath heretofore coutched vp in ſecreſie: For beit knowne, that the mighty Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> an auntient enemie vnto your Crowne and dignitie, is familiarly crept into ſecret fauour with Queene <hi>Katherne</hi> your honourable Spouſe, who vnder ſhadow of ſeruiceable dutie, bereaueth your Maieſtie from the fruite of true continencie, and couereth your nuptiall bed with a ſtrayned mantle of blacke
<pb facs="tcp:6036:5"/>infamie: Oh what a griefe is this vnto the ſoules of vs, which intirely loue your Maieſtie, whoſe liues be wholely conſecrated to your good fortunes. It is not ſpight that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth me to defame the reputation of your royal Queene, vnto whom I ſtand bound in all humble ſeruice: nor any hate, nor proffered miuryes, doth inflame my minde to blemiſh the good Duke of <hi>Suffolkes</hi> fame with immortall ignobilletie, but loue and dutie to my Prince and countrey: wherefore (moſt noble King) cleare your vnderſtanding, and weede from your Court ſuch treacherous deceauers, that your life be not ſodainely intrapped, and we vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatly depriued of a wiſe and puiſant Prince. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, if I <hi>George de Cambria Barron of Buckingam,</hi> be diſproued or polluted with the breach of diſhoneſty, an vtterer of falſe ſpeaches, or be found a flatterer, or one that hunteth after Princely fauour, proudly aſpiring after dignetyes and promotions, then let me periſh, and like a traytor be throwne out as an open ſhame vnto the world: otherwiſe, knit and binde me to your Maieſtie in the faſt bond of loyallty, and haue the reward of a faythfull ſubiect.</p>
               <p>When the Barron had thus inchaunted King <hi>Edwards</hi> eares, his head burned more hotter with the heate of ieloſie then before: a diſſeaſe ſo incurable, that being once entered into the mind, neuer reſteth till it penitrateth into the ſecret deapth of the hart. The King thus catcht in a fooles net, neclected honeſt trueth, and was choaked with the ſweete baight of flatterie: and being vnable to diſcharge the boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heate of his ſtomacke, with exſtreame outrage called for the Lord high Marſhall of England, and commaunded him to take a ſtrong Garriſon of beſt tryed marſhall Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and to apprehend the Queene, and the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and keepe them both in ſafe cuſtody, vntill he knew his further pleaſure: which ſharpe commaundement
<pb facs="tcp:6036:5"/>was preſently put in execution by the Marſhall, who in hart greatly lamented the diſhonour of ſo vertuous a Queene. But now the King like one being ſcandalizde by his wiues infidelitie, departed into his chamber, where many a day he ſecluded him ſelfe from all company, except the wicked Barron, which continually encreaſed his Ieloſie: in which hell of lyfe, we will leaue him for a ſpace, and ſpeake of the Queenes extremitie, being impriſoned vnder the Lord high Parſhals guard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> ¶ How the three Earles, of Weſtmerland, Sommerſet, and Durham, came to viſite Queene Katherine, being in Priſon: and what paſſed betwixt them.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> ſeeing himſelfe ſo wrongfully impriſned, and ſuch falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations layde againſt the honour of his reputation, was ſtroken into ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine amaze, that he could not outwardly bewray his ſorrow, but as it were inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleed teares of blood, to cleare his conſcience before the immortall Maieſtie of God for ſuch a crime.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, the noble guiltleſſe Queene, oppreſſed with like woe and mortall miſhappe, beholding her ſelfe a ſpectacle of diſhonour to the worlde, although before the ſupernall Iudge moſt cleare and perfect in conſcience, without either ſtaine or ſpot of defamation: yet being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed
<pb facs="tcp:6036:6"/>plexed with ſundry thoughtes of griefe, procured by the furious frownes of her Husbandes hate, in the time of her impriſonment, writ theſe verſes vpon the walles with the blood of her marriage finger.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſpightfull Barrons curſed flatterie,</l>
                     <l>Hath wrongd Queene Katherines ſpotleſſe chaſtetie:</l>
                     <l>And leueld out his dartes of laſting ſhame,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the princely honours of her fame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But Trueth in time, ſhall conquer Enuies will,</l>
                     <l>Where Fayth ſhall ſpring, and brightly flooriſh ſtill:</l>
                     <l>Packe hence Diſpaire, ſweete Ioy come eaſe my ſmart,</l>
                     <l>For conſtant Fayth doth harbour in my hart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Loue is true, my ſpouſall Promiſe iuſt,</l>
                     <l>Not ſtaind with any crime of lawles luſt:</l>
                     <l>Then princely EDWARD, ceaſe thy cruell hare,</l>
                     <l>For Falſhood wronges my noble fame and ſtate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Deare Spouſe, deſpiſe not thus thy conſtant Queene,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe loyaltie doth gliſter bright and greene:</l>
                     <l>If euer you tooke pleaſure in my youth,</l>
                     <l>Let ſound beliefe be witnes of my truth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>No ſooner had the Queene finiſhed theſe bloody lines, but there came into the Priſon to comfort her, three graue Counſellers of King <hi>Edwards</hi> Court, whom ſhe did moſt louingly entertaine: and after ſome conference paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, ſhe moſt kindly kiſſed her Husbandes liuely Picture, which as then hanged about her necke by a faire chaine or rundle of Gold, powring out many bitter teares, to the wonderful griefe &amp; admiration of all that beheld her: the which being done, ſhe humbly deſired pardon of the Lords, to vſe ſome words in the defence of her chaſtetie, ſo that ſhe might not abuſe their patience: and as ſhe hauing
<pb facs="tcp:6036:6"/>an innocent &amp; guiltleſſe hart, ſo ſhe might freely diſcharge her conſcience, and cleare her ſelfe from all thoſe vniuſt accuſations layde againſt her.</p>
               <p>This her vertuous requeſt ſo highly pleaſed the three Lords, that they preſently conſented to giue her free autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie openly to honeſt her honorable and auncient credite. The harmeles Queene in a moſt ſeueere and bolde counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with ſundry taire amiable ſyrtes in her checkes, her browes beſet like the maieſtie of <hi>Diana,</hi> her white iuorte trembling hands like the driuen ſnow, her body euen fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and faſhioned of the virgin waxe, ſpake as foloweth.</p>
               <p>If vnmeaſurable griefe of hart (Right honorable Lords) or the noble blood of my predeceſſors, may be ſufficient to draw melting pittie from your mindes, I doe not doubt but your wiſedomes will accompt the accuſation of the wicked Barron to be vniuſt, which he hath oppreſſed me withall, who dayly ſeekes by flatterie, to cut the ſweete ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and tender greeneſſe of my young yeeres: therefore (moſt noble Lordes) for pitties ſake, arme me from his hurtes, defende and guard me from his dreadfull conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſuccour and ſupport me with honourable iuſtice: for he doth aſſault me with miſerie, he doth vſurpe tirannicall villanie againſt me, he ſeeketh the ouerthrow of the Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorie of our Kingdome, he ſetteth a deuiſton betwixt my Lord and me, and doth prepare an entraunce for himſelfe: But I wiſh a ſeperation of ſoule, with a thouſande tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of body, if euer I ouerturned my ſpouſall chaſtetie, the which I haue alwayes carefully kept, and without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation preterued it to my deare Lord and Husband. If then theſe my wordes may mollefie your hartes, to pleade in my behalfe to Kind <hi>Edward</hi> that he may with diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſider my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cencie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> repute you mercifull men, and ſound ſearchers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: wherefore, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:6036:7"/>vpon me I ſay, haue mercie vpon a wronged Queene, trayterouſly abuſed. And in ſpeaking this, teares ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly flowed from the cundets of her eyes, that ſhe was forced to be ſilent.</p>
               <p>Theſe wordes of Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> ſo greeued their hartes, that they were all perſwaded of her vertuous lyfe, and that her honourable fame was iniured through the bengance of the aſpyring Barron, who by flatterie had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted King <hi>Edwards</hi> noble minde: therefore to comfort the greeued Queene, the worthy Earle of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> in the name of all the reſt, ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>Your modeſtie (moſt noble Queene, quoth he) ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force vs to proſtrate our ſelues before his Maieſtie, that he may fauourably infranchize your lipertie, and take you againe to his good grace and well likeing, whoſe head (no doubt) is fraughted with many fantaſies againſt you: but yet ſince humilitie doth illuſtrate and aduance your cauſe with open trueth, reſolue this a comfort to your princely minde, that your enemie which hath ſo mightely abuſed your reputation, can neuer eſcape due puniſhment: and the Gods (I know) will neuer forgiue ſo vile a wickedneſſe: As for example. <hi>Camera</hi> the Queene of <hi>Egypt,</hi> hauing a hundred thouſand ſorrowes lodged in her chaſt minde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by rigorous iuſtice condemned to be torne a ſunder by wilde Horſes, and ſo made a dolorous example vnto the worlde: But now marke the iudgementes of God vpon the vile betrayers of this vertuous Queene: for euen in the hower of her death, an hoaſt or armie of angry Waſpes with the ſharpe ſtinges in their tayles, in open view de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and ſubuerted her enemies: an exployte of worthy warning againſt all falſe pertured accuſers, and ſodaine ſeueritie againſt ſuch as exerciſe by tyrranic all fury, to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Princes eares.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:7"/>Let not me forget the noble Egyptian <hi>Panteron,</hi> which made a law, that whoſoeuer vowed a falſe oath, ſhould be led and ſlayne as a Caulfe in the ſhambles, his ſkinne fleade of, his head ſet up as a ſigne of a murtherer, a rauiſher of holy chaſtety, and his corpes throwne to the kinges Houndes to be deuoured.</p>
               <p>Infinite examples might be remembred, amongſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant floriſhing Ladyes, that haue been inſpired with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent guiftes of vertue. I could diſcourſe manifolde war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: but chiefly I will prefixe before your eyes the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, teares, and vnmeaſurable forrowes of Lady <hi>Aelana,</hi> a paragon and mirrour of true continency, whoſe portion was vexation and vnreſtfulneſſe, cruelly bereft from chaſt integrety, and renowned honour: but ſuch was the proofe of her rare and exqueſite vertue, by the fauorable Gods, that greedy Beares (as Lieftenants of Iuſtice) deuowred her enemies.</p>
               <p>Thus, if right were not mayntayned by immortall meanes, violence, diſſimulation, and deceitfull flatterers, would floriſh amongſt mortall men, to the ſubuertion of Kingdomes, inquiatations of Kings houſes, tirrable cryes in iudgement ſeates, diſtruction of Citties, and ouerturning of common wealthes: wherefore (moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Princeſſe) if the righteous honeſty of your cauſe be buylded vpon a ſure rocke, mercy ſhalbe gayned, mallice vanquiſhed by modeſty, and thraldome depriued by liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: thus reſting our ſelues with this reſolution, till King <hi>Edwards</hi> minde and pleaſure be further knowne herein.</p>
               <p>After this kind promiſe pronounced by the good Earle of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> the Queene pulled from her golden locks certaine ſumptious pearles, &amp; rich iewels, hanging in moſt beautifull brightnes, and gaue them to the Earle of <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet,</hi> ſaying. I doe not (right honortable Lord) impart
<pb facs="tcp:6036:8"/>theſe guyftes as a bribe couertly to ballance my cauſe, but as a proofe of my good will, and a requital of your paines, in viſiting me thus in my miſeries: which if they be grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accepted, I ſhal thinke my ſelfe moſt highly honored.</p>
               <p>No ſooner were theſe ſpeaches finiſhed, and thankes giuen for the Queenes gentle Rewardes, but the Nobles departed the Priſon, and conueiged them ſelues into a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Chamber, where euery one deliuered his opinion, meaſuring out a direct meanes for her enlargment: all which proceeded of true loue, and firme beliefe of her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtetie. But after many conſultations, with a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they concluded to write vnto the King, not onely to alter his diſcontented minde, but to diſcouer the falſehood and flatterie of the wicked Barron.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Counſels Supplication to King Edward.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF vnfaigned affections which loyall Subiectes beare to the Common-wealth of England, or the true chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of your Queene vniuſtly wronged by flatterie, may mooue you (moſt excellent Prince) to remember the holy vow of Wedlocke, where your inſeperable loues were ioyned together, and of two perſons made but one body; we aſſure our ſelues then, that your vertue and wiſedome will lenefie the honourable cauſe of your nuptiall Spouſe, and gather theſe vnioynied members into right courſe againe: For why ſhould your Grace be diſmembred, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all the partes of naturall proportion redefied in your perſon? Why ſhould you make your felfe a poynting ſtocke of infamie to forraigne enemies, and a domeſticall contempt to your owne Subiectes? Let naturall regard
<pb facs="tcp:6036:8"/>perſwade you, to driue out theſe pernitious poyſons, which flattering Subiectes haue lodged in your breaſt, inchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you with vncurable Ieloſie; which except you ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely reforme, your Royall eſtate may fall into preſent ruine. Theſe dangers conſidered, lyeth you vpon ſpeede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to frequent the companie of your chaſt Queene, whoſe honourable vndefiled foote-ſteppes we haue made good tryall of, to the hope of your fauour, her ſpeedie deliuerie, and a iuſt diſcharge of our dueties.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Supplication receiued by the King, could no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all preuaile to enlarge her ſeruitude: for a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the wicked Barron had preſented to King <hi>Edward</hi> a Gold-ſmithes daughter of London, named <hi>Caſiope;</hi> a Damſell of a lewde behauiour, yet beautifull and paſſing amorous, who with her flattering ſmiles ſo intangled his eyes, and bewitcht his fancie in ſuch ſort, that he delighted onely in her companie, wholly changing his auntient loue from his loyall Queene, thinking all times too long, till the tender thred of her lyfe were cut off, which Vertue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time, had ſo honourably ſpunne.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Edwards</hi> minde being thus obſcured with thicke fogges of flatterie, and ouerwhelmed into a pernitious gulfe of darkneſſe, his diſeaſe of Ieloſie prooued more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable: which could neither be holpen through the earneſt loue of his Queene, nor perſwaded through the long ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of learned Counſellers.</p>
                  <p>Oh, it is a worlde to beholde, how flattering deceiuers can temper deſlicate drinkes for euery mans appetite, ſtoppe wiſedomes eares by falſe inchauntments, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert true conſcience by wrongfull inſinuation. The King on the other ſide, miſtruſted not vulgar reports of populer
<pb facs="tcp:6036:9"/>men, neither the ouerthrow of his Kingdome by ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſion, nor regarded the patient minde of his vertuous Queene, called for certaine of his priuie Counſell: who being comde before him, he gaue them this ſharpe ediet for the arraignement and ſentence againſt Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Suffolke:</hi> the tenure of the Kings words were as followeth.</p>
                  <p>If wilde Iuie (my noble Lordes) ruinate the walles of my Houſe, reaching within the windowes of my ſecret Chamber, were it not neceſſarie to be plucked vp: If in pleaſant Gardens one ſpreading Weede diſorder all the other odoriferous Flowers, is it not requiſite to haue it deſtroyed: And although the rare beautie, and excellent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niamentes of my Queene might eaſely inflame ſimple minde, to beleeue her faigned holyneſſe: yet one filthie ſtayne blemiſheth all the reſt. One wrintle in <hi>Apelles</hi> tinſell, blurred the coſtly Tables of <hi>Bacchus.</hi> Doth not one vnſauery corner peſter a whole Houſe? One lothfome odoure ouercome many pretious Oyntmentes? Why are you then my Lordes, ſo blinded with her deceitfull practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, plagued with her deſembling wordes, and alured with her peſtilent poyſons? What, do you repute her a demie God? Doe you thinke her an Angell of heauen? Is ſhe twiſe bleſt, &amp; my ſelfe a thouſand times accurſt? I ſweare by the honoure of my Scepter, to puniſh her lewd lyfe in ſuch a maner, that neuer after the blacke cloudes of her ſhame, may obſcure the glory of my Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Let it not therefore (moſt noble Lordes) be imagined, that I can be ouercome by any mans flatterie, or my wits ſo lightly carryed away, to be deceyued without good and due proofe: all which great iniuries to my perſon, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment to my Kingdome, and wrong to my Subiects, ſhall be followes with ſeueere iudgement: therefore, I
<pb facs="tcp:6036:9"/>charge you vpon your dueties, as you hope to winne the garland of my fauour, to proſecute my determination: which is, the deſertfull fall of my vntruſty Queene, and the confuſion of her proude minnion the Duke of <hi>Suffolke.</hi> And in ſaying this, lyke one wholly bent to a reſolute will, not ſtaying for any anſwere, he departed from his Lordes, and left them euery one ſodaynely ſurpryſed with griefe, ready to caſt them ſelues headlong into the deſartes of diſpaire: yet durſt they not by any meanes ſeeke to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his will, but preſently to perſeuecre in this ſiniſter iudgement.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> ¶ How the Queene and the Duke of Suffolke were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned and condemned of adultrie, through falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses, and what after happened.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He very next morning after King <hi>Edward</hi> had giuen charge for their arraignment, were they called foorth before certaine of the honourable Lords of the priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and were tryed vpon the proofe of their accuſation: where, the wicked Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Buckingam,</hi> with two other bace Gentlemen of the Kinges Court, did ſweare by the immortall powers of heauen, that the filthy fact of adultrie was committed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the honour of his Maieſties perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:10"/>After which deteſtable oath falſely proteſted, the good Earle of <hi>Sommerſet</hi> ſtood vp in open audience, and with a diſchearefull countenance, ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>Oh you wretched betrayers of Innocent blood (quoth he) although they taſte the bitter to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mentes in this worlde, yet I feare not but they will ſhortly wander to that celeſtiall Paradice, from whence will deſcend fierie vengance vpon your heades. Oh you Diuels and Feendes of impietie, woe worth the time that euer you attempted ſo vile a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie: for you haue taken a vertuous Queene from vs, a Queene that is the merrour of true continencie, and onely patterne of a conſtant woman: the lyke clamor and pittifull lamentation was in the whole Countrey rounde about. Then in the middeſt of which ſorrowfull moane, the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> deſired the Counſellours and Iudges, that he might vtter ſome ſpeaches in his owne behalfe, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to diſcharge his conſcience of the vile acte his accuſer had layde againſt his lyfe: his ſpeaches were in this maner deliuered.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant (right Honorable aſſemblie) that this my tender body clothed with Innocencie, muſt ſhortly be diſcharged from the priſon of this worlde, and muſt take my iourney vp to heauen for true protection, for this lyfe is nothing but a wandering pilgrimage of woe, a mercileſſe ſea, which often times vomiteth vs into the mouth of pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pirates, daſhing vs vpon many dangerous Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks: and now ſince my duetie tyeth me to ſolemnize an honorable memorie of this aflicted Queene, deliuer out a true diſcharge of her chaſtetie, and a preſeruation of mine owne honeſtie: For if euer I preſumed ſuch a deede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the maieſtie of her worthy perſon, let this Ghoſt of mine be deliuered a paſture for infernall woormes to gnaw vpon; or, if my ſenſes had been ſo arrogantly diſpoſed,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:10"/>her vertues might haue eaſely kilde my deſiers, yea and diſcloſed the ſame, to my vtter ruine and confuſion. But I ſee my proffered diligence lyke a truſty Seruant, proffered to her commaundement, hath brought this woe vpon vs both: therefore, if her fame be brought in queſtion through my miſuſage, or if the proude Barron enuiouſly thirſting for my blood, hath thus wrongfully damnified my gratious Princeſſe, let a doble death for her deliuerance, be layde vpon my lyfe: let my ſorrowes be twice imbrewed, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh her paynes: let the ranſome of her pictie be layde vpon my body, a graue and pit to finiſh vp her ſorrowes.</p>
               <p>Now this I ſpeake as a witneſſe of my laſt will, hauing enioyed this worlde twentie ſixe yeeres, ſufficiently proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the vanities thereof, and now willing to reſigne this lyfe to a more better hope: and as my young forepaſſed lyfe is free from ſtaine, ſo will I neuer bluſh nor hide my face, as one ſuſpected, or blotted with any ſuch crime, of which I am now condemned of.</p>
               <p>With theſe wordes (pronounced by the Duke of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke</hi>) was the Earle of <hi>Sommerſet</hi> depriued of ſpeach, and for the inwarde griefe which ſwelled in his breaſt, he could not vtter any one worde: humane ſorrow powred downe from his eyes abundant ſtreames of teares, manifeſting the good will and true affection he bore to trueth and iuſtice, his ſoule grecued that true honour nurſed vp to ripe age, ſhould in a ſhort moment be deliuered to a cruell and moſt vntimely death.</p>
               <p>But the Earle of <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> (which as then preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Kinges perſon) hauing ſomewhat a more chearefull hart, ſtoode vp in the Iudgement ſeate, and ſpake as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>Moſt gracious Queene (quoth he) and you my honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> know, that we in Iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:6036:11"/>cannot releaſe, nor helpe your miſeries, for it behooueth vs to fulfill the Kinges commaundement, leaſt we incurre diſpleaſure to our ſelues, hindering vs, and nothing furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you: but yet this remedy in my conceite ſtandes with iuſtice, that you my Lord of <hi>Suffolke</hi> may reobtaine your honourable fame, challenging a combat of the wicked Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and ſo reueale to the worlde your giltleſſe perfection: for he in preſence of vs all, hath ſpit out moſt vile wordes of deſpight, blemiſhing and ouerthrowing your credite: euen ſo notea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e before the face of men, your true intencion and reſpect to honour: and to the ſame effect, frameman humble Supplication to his Maieſtie: and in doing ſo, we the eſtates of this land heare preſent, will eternally crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle your endeuours to after ages. And in ſpeaking theſe wordes, the whole Counſell brooke vp court for that day, and departed euery one ſeuerally to their lodginges: the Queene and the Duke, were conducted againe to their wonted captiuitie, whereas the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> greatly comforted with this counſell, thought euery day a yeere, vntill he had giuen the challendge, and that the Barron was prouoked to the combat: ſo taking pen and incke, he writ this knightly petition to his Maieſtie.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Duke of Suffolkes challenge of combat, ſent to King Edward.</head>
                     <p>IF your royall perſon (moſt mighty Prince) hath bin wronged thorow my counterfeite ſeruice, let me be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached with the ſcourge of penall iudgment, ſo that reaſonable deſiers be firſt fauoured: for now honour burning hot in the cloſure of my hart, in tryall of my honeſty, doth craue this permisſion at your princely
<pb facs="tcp:6036:11"/>handes, that I may combat with the miſchieuous varlet, and falſe flatterer, the proud Barron of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> in diſproofe of his cloaked falſehood. If my quarrell be vniuſt, the eternall powers of heauen will not proſper it: If his ground-worke be well layde, and haue a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, his intent will be expreſſed the better. For he that dares commit theſe wronges openly, will not be abaſhed to auow them openly. He that launcheth in the puddle of diſcord, knoweth a cleare paſsage how to eſcape: therefore (moſt noble Prince) let the holy fountaine of mercifull pittie ſtraine out, that it may mooue your Grace, to graunt my requeſtes: I ende.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>By me the ſorrowfull and deſſolate Duke of Suffolke.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> receiuing this Supplication, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Challenge, thought it a deadly bane prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Barron of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> lyfe, yet he iudged the deniall of it would greatly preiudice his dignitie: ſo deſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling an outward reſpect to honour, though inwardly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring fraudulent deceipt, he with a ſmiling countenance made motion of the combat to the Barron, as well for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of fame, as publiſhing of fayth. The Barron ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his owne inſufficiencie, being loth to performe the Combat, was aſtoniſhed at the Kinges requeſt, and ſtroken into ſodaine dumpes, like one that had loſt his ſpeach: but yet after a great pauſe, and long ſtay, he ſpake in this maner.</p>
               <p>I will not refuſe (ſayd he) the accompliſhment of any thing commaunded by your Maieſtie, although your will and pleaſure herein ſeemeth ſtrange and vniuſt, in that a
<pb facs="tcp:6036:12"/>true Subiecte ſhould hazard his lyfe with a falſe Traytor. The Barron ſometimes ſilent, ſometimes ouer talcatiue: ſometimes luſty, ſometimes a coward: ſo that ſtanding betweene fraude and feare, he fayntly repreſented an offer. Vpon this, the King procured a day of Combat, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhed throughout the whole land this proclamation that followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I EDWARD, by long ſufferance of diuine fortune, King, Prince, and chiefe Ruler of all the partes of England. &amp;c. Whereas the determined purpoſe of the noble and hardy Gentleman the <hi>Lord Barron of Buckingam,</hi> is to defende himſelfe againſt the miſerable and condemned catiue the <hi>Duke of Suffolke,</hi> a fable for the worlde to gaze vpon, an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous wretch of notable diſhonour, harbouring in his hart long Treaſons againſt our Perſon, Subiectes, and dominion: in excuſe of his leawde lyfe, for his beſt aduantage, challengeth open warre againſt my good Subiect the <hi>Lord Barron:</hi> vnto whoſe requeſt, in fauour of auntient proweſſe, I haue yeelded. But as touching the treſpaſſe of my Queene, no Combat ſhall preuaile to acquite her diſgrace, nor no mortall benefites pardone her offences. Thus fare you well.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Edward of England.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:12"/>Thus did the King thinke no paynes ill beſtowed that might bring her in hatred of the common people, and alſo very much thirſted after her blood, through the perſwaſion of his vnchaſt Curtizan faire <hi>Caſiope,</hi> that euery day ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his lippes with ſo many kiſſes, as her ſute could neither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be fruſtrated, nor at no time forgotten.</p>
               <p>The Barron, and he likewiſe, roued in a vnetie of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, and did priuely hyer a kitchen drudge, named <hi>Truſtie Thomas,</hi> a ſlaue full of pouertie, yet a luſty tall fellow, glad to obtaine the Kinges fauour by accomply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng of any exployt for gayue: who in receipt of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes, tooke vpon him the name and perſon of the Barron of <hi>Buckingam,</hi> to fight the combat with the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> being of equall proportion and ſtature. This <hi>Truſtie Thomas</hi> had free libertie to make choyce in the Kinges Armorie, fitting him ſelfe beſt for his defence in the ſureſt coate of Steele, and the like paſſage into the Kinges Stable for the choyce of the moſt couragious Courſer. Thus furniſhed in moſt ſeemely order, for the gayne of money, was content to commit himſelfe to the mallice of fortunes hate.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> on the other ſide, as well furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in all reſpectes, nothing doubted the good ſucceſſe of his aduenture, being borne of a Noble famelie, valiant, and well exerciſed in the feates of Armes, reputed for the goodlyeſt Gentleman in the vniuerſall countrey of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: ſo laying aſide his courtly delightes vſed in the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming time of his youth, and putting on inuincible firme and approued magnanimitie of body, he came the nyght before the Combat ſhould be tryed, to Queene <hi>Katherines</hi> chamber window, being both priſoners in one Tower, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a wall betweene their ſeberall lodginges, where as the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> ſung thefe verſes folowing.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:13"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Reuenge, ring out thy knell, let trueth appeare,</l>
                     <l>To change my bitter Springes to Waters cleare:</l>
                     <l>Goe packe Diſpaire, thy ſight I doe diſdaine,</l>
                     <l>My Knightly deedes, bright Honour ſhall obtaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Faint Feare, diſlodge thee from my noble breſt,</l>
                     <l>Thou art no friende of mine, nor wiſhed gueſt:</l>
                     <l>For coward Captaines wins no ſtately Fortes,</l>
                     <l>Nor rotten Barke arriues in pleaſant Portes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aſſurance tels the ſecrets of my hart</l>
                     <l>That Falſehood ſhall receaue his due deſart:</l>
                     <l>Proud Enuie then ſhall not obſcure the light,</l>
                     <l>Of Honours brightneſſe, with his hatefull ſpight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh ſacred Heauens, accompliſh my deſier!</l>
                     <l>That I may quench the heate of enuies fier:</l>
                     <l>Whereby my ſad and diſcontented minde,</l>
                     <l>May gentle ſolace and ſweete comfort finde.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>This ſorrowfull Songue ſtroke ſuch a paſſion to the Queenes hart, like one deſpiſing this vaine lyfe, that ſhe deſired dolefull death haſtely to finiſh her callamities: but yet bearing a Princely minde, in ſome meaſure to requite the Dukes curteſie, ſhe anſwered hun with theſe Verſes following.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Queene Katherines Song to the <hi>Duke of Suffolke.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Good lucke conduckt thy minde vnto content,</l>
                     <l>To conquer him, that is ſo lewdly bent,</l>
                     <l>To ſet deuiſion betwixt my Lord and me,</l>
                     <l>In ſpoyling of my blooming chaſtetie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6036:13"/>
                     <l>Stay ſtately Pride, climbe vp thy ſteps no higer,</l>
                     <l>But ſoone diſgorge thy hot ambitious fier:</l>
                     <l>For if Queene Katherine euer lyued ſo,</l>
                     <l>Let grauelled Graue be cradle for her woe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Suſpition, leaue to vexe ſuch worthy wightes,</l>
                     <l>Which ſpendes their dayes in vertues ſweete delightes.</l>
                     <l>Nor let the crucltie of ſpightfull foes</l>
                     <l>Plant vp a Docke, vnroote a ſmelling Roſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictorious pome will ſhortly ſeeke to crowne,</l>
                     <l>Thy princely browes with garlandes of renowne;</l>
                     <l>Which euermore ſhall ſpring and floriſh greene,</l>
                     <l>For thus defending of a wronged Queene.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>In this, or ſuch lyke maner, ſpent they the night away, to the exceeding comfort of each other, vntyll the radient beautie of the next morning began to glifter in the eaſterne worlde, which cauſed them then to take leaue of each other: for at that ſame inſtant, the Lord high Marſhall in ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne iuſtice, called foorth the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> to auow his prize of Combat, hauing ten olde ſage Fathers going before him in mourning Gownes, and white Wandes in their handes, lyke one that went to fetch away the golden Garland of renowne: and comming to the place appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he met <hi>Truſtie Thomas,</hi> as defendant, in ſtead of the proude Barron: vnto whom, with a boulde courage he ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>Ah thou falſe Traytor, ſpoyler of true honour, thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamefaſt butcher of innocent blood: Can nothing quench thy inſatiate thirſt of flatterie, but the guyltleſſe blood of Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> and my lyfe: I doubt not, but thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:6036:14"/>purchaſed a iuſt reuenge for thy infamous wickedneſſe: thou at this preſent ſeekeſt after honorable fame, but the Gods, I hope, will caſt thy corpes vnto the moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyeſt vermine of the earth to pray vpon. Thou feedeſt thy ſelfe with falſe honour, but perpetuall ſhame ſhalbe thy beſt reward. Doth not thy hart throbbe at this enterprize? And doth not thy conſcience declare thy impietie? It would be a moſt ſeemely thing before any blow paſſe betwixt vs, that thou with ſharpe penaunce reconcile thy ſelfe vnto the Gods, to haue a comfortable ioy after this lyfe: for there is ſuch inumcible manhood ſealed in my hart, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of thy blood ſhall acquite thy villanie.</p>
               <p>The ſimple ſlaue in hearing this knightly reſolution, was ſo amazed, that with more willingneſſe he was ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vp his Marſhals ſtaffe, then defend the enterpriſe taken in hand.</p>
               <p>But the Duke with valtant magnanimitie haſtely bucklde on his enemie, bleſſing him with ſound blowes, as if he ſhould ſay, now is the time eyther of winning or looſing honour: now, eyther the ſpot of diſhonour ſhall blurre me, or the ſhyning light of renowne cleare me for euer. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſixe blowes the Combat ended, and <hi>Truſtie Thomas</hi> hanged dead in his ſteele Saddle, grouelyng and fooming, with his necke broken: whereat the people with wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full admiration ſhooted, and cauſed Drummes and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets to be ſounded, in ſigne of victorie.</p>
               <p>But a litle before the Combat began, the King gaue the Lord Marſhall this charge, that if the Defendant tooke the foyle, his Armour ſhould not be vnbuckled, nor the dead coarſe diſcouered, except it were in his preſence. The Marſhall as well to accompliſh the Kinges pleaſure, as a full diſcharge of his office, cauſed the ſayd dead body to be tranſported before the King: vpon whoſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:14"/>certayne <hi>Dominick</hi> Fryers (ſworne to the ſame effect) immediatly burned the Peaſaunts filthy corpes, promyſing them rich rewardes, and great promotions for their faythfull ſeruice ſhewed therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> ¶ How the Duke of Suffolke was baniſhed England, and Queene Katherine condemned to die, with other thinges that happened.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the victorious Duke in plaine troth thought his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie dead and vanquiſhe: and when that he expected releaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he had his calamities the more increaſed. For the King being ſturred vp with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt him, and fearing leaſt this bace enterprize ſhould be bruted to the eares of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, to his vtter diſgrace and infamie, he gaue this requitall to the victorious Cumbitant, and committed by vniuerſall proclamation, that the good Duke ſhould within two dayes be baniſhed not onely the Court, but alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:6036:15"/>boundes and territories of England, with all his Lordly poſſeſſions, landes, reuenewes, rentes, fees, inheritaunces, but alſo from his kindred, friendes, and acquaintance. Which heauie and vnprincely iudgement, did not onely trouble his thoughtes, but greeued the hart of gratious Queene <hi>Katherine:</hi> that although ſhe was not deſtitute of many ſinguler good friendes, yet bereft of her beſt friende, the onely ſtaffe of her lyfe: the loſſe of whoſe company, ſtroke ſuch an extreame ſorrow vnto her hart, that ſhe lyued lyke one without a ſoule, weary of the worlde, and all other pleaſures, which as then did but ſmally comforther.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> an houre before the tune of his departure, came to the Queenes lodging to take his leaue: who gaue him a Hoope of gold, round faſtened to his necke: the Poſie about the ſame was this.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>What earthly place ſo euer harbours thee,</l>
                  <l>Till death depart (braue Lord) remember mee.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The which being claſped about his necke with two ſiluer claſpes prepared for the ſame purpoſe, whereon was very curiouſly ingraued two bloody Hartes bounde togither with a True-loues-knot: with many interrupted ſighes and panting ſtomackes, departed they the one from the other, to the great griefe of all the beholders there preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But within an houre after the Dukes departure, the King directed his letters to the Lord high Marſhall, that within two dayes following, the Queene ſhould be behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Which heauie newes, and tyrannicall furie, diſpleaſed the mindes of the whole Countrey: for the Kinges vitious lyfe was manifeſted to euery man; beſides, the common people of England caſt their eyes to the multitude of falſe flatterers, which continually haunted the Kinges Court, euery man ſeruing his owne will, glutting in pride, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:15"/>and whoredome: reaching and rouing after ſtately honour, ſeathering and warming their neſſes, whiſtling merry ſonges in the Kings eare, and feeding the world with pleaſant delightes: beſides that, many deſperate Ruffines were harbored about the Kings perſon, whereby euery man became lawleſſe to liue as he lyſted: yet many noble Lordes, vertuous, wiſe, and learned Iudges, of his Maieſties priuie Counſell, inwardly mourned the ſtate and time they liued in, by which meanes the commones loues were drawne to the Queenes ſaueguard, ſo that ſhe wanted no prayers, good will, nor earneſt ſute for her deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: the more her forrowes encreaſed, the greater was ſhe fauaured.</p>
               <p>The King hereby fell to extreame hatred, thorow his vniuerſall Dominion, and euery man redely held vp his weapon to pull the Princely Scepter out of his handes: And whilſt he expected the Queenes execution, a preſent meſſage was returned him, that ſhe was with childe, (all which being true) yet Ieloſie hauing ſo much power in his vnruly ſenſes, that he could neither alter his preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, nor find a reſting place for his vnquiet thoughts, nor holſome counſell to eure the diſſeaſe of his minde: which tiranicall reſolution being wholly bent to the confuſion of the gratious Queene, chieſly incenſed through his Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines ſmiling beautie: on whoſe poyſoned ſweetnes he now baighted &amp; ſed vpon, did rather apply with curteſie to her humor, then to repriue his Queene from her appoynted execution: which reſolute purpoſe, when the good Earle of <hi>Sommerſet</hi> vnderſtood, as well to content ſundry other Lordes, being partners in the cauſe, as the purchaſing of ciuell tranquillety to the Kingdome, made this oration to King <hi>Edward:</hi> the effect following.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:16"/>
                  <head>¶ The Earle of Sommerſets Oration to King Edward, for the Queenes repriue.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NO greater ornament of glorie (moſt mightie King) may adorne your royall Maieſtie, then to reuert to your Princely eſtate, magnificence, Iuſtice, and clemencie, (the onely ſtandard of protection which all your Subiects muſt reſt vpon) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let wiſedome perſwade you, to make a conqueſt of thoſe vices, which in the eyes of the word are apparent, for your Subiects in generall, repute your honourable deare ſpouſe and vertuous Queene: but your Princely opinion (by flatterers enuie) is hardly perſwaded: which if it be continued, will in the end greedely van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh and leaue you a common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>oty to the world. And further more, your common people grudge that your worthy Queene, hath bin ſo nearely examined, wroungfully impriſoned, ſhamefully araigned, hatefully handled, cruelly condemned, and without ſparke of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour adiudged to die. Alſo, they report that the good Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of <hi>Suffolke</hi> (being victor in the Combat) is againſt law and iuſtice, baniſhed the land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All theſe ſtrange cuſtomes (moſt noble Prince) is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iculous to your gouernment, and offenſiue to your people: and ſince your Queene is falſely accuſed, miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and belyed, it were a royall glory, onely for hope of poſteritie, that your vertuous Spouſe were repriued. If you hacke downe the tree, firſt ſaue the fruie: If you graſpe vp the gallant flowers, conſerue the ſeedes: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you regard your deſſent, royallice your name and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie: otherwiſe you ouerthrow your princely Throne, Seate, and Scepter for euer. As I proteſt (vttering my
<pb facs="tcp:6036:16"/>wordes before the ſupernall Iudge of heauen) that the chaſt body of Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> is pure, vntouched from all deſpight of villanie. So (moſt noble Prince) take her againe into your fauour, adorne your princely Throne with her beautifull countenance, recouer your royall name, weede from your Court theſe faigned flatterers, gaping ambitiouſly after gaine: diſcouer the morninges light, and cut the loftie hilles that ouerſhadow your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſprings. Be not perſwaded, but that the fruite which her body hath formed, from your Maieſties loynes firſt iſſued, is rightly planted, and of a perfect of spring, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> (vpon waightie affaires) was ſent Ambaſſadoure into <hi>Normandie</hi> in the time of your Queenes conception, long before, &amp; many weekes after.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therfore I doubt not (moſt excellent Prince) but theſe my ſpeaches may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>llifie your hart, and procure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pittie to appeare; and in doing ſo, humanetie, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, and noble worthineſſe, ſhall illuſtrate your perſon, and with pregnant pollecie odorne your high eſtate and Imnage: a rare bloſſome ſprouting out, to the exceeding comfort of all England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King being reſolued (at this the Earle of <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſets</hi> requeſt, with the perſwaſion of diuers other noble men) to graunt her repriuement, vntill her deliuerance of childbirth were accompliſhed, ſo that his deſier in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her to death, might not afterward be hindred.</p>
                  <p>This her repriuement did not ſo much reioyce the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull heartes of the Engliſh Lords, as it bred anger and diſcontentment in the Barron of <hi>Buckingames</hi> breaſt, who imbouldned <hi>Caſiope</hi> the Kinges Concubine, to call for the Queenes ſecret diſtruction, greatly miſtruſting that continuall windes would at length ſhake the Tower of
<pb facs="tcp:6036:17"/>their proſperiites. The beautie of this fayre <hi>Caſiope</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the eyes of King <hi>Edward</hi> a little earthly Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, which chaunged his inclinations to any way ſhee pleaſed: for what ſoeuer he openly promiſed to his Nobles, would he ſecretly denie before <hi>Caſiope:</hi> and what ſoeuer was obtayned contrary to her good liking, was contiually croſſed with a bad ſucceſſe.</p>
                  <p>This coſtly magnificent Lady, thus vndermined high mountaines, builded bridges ouer mighty Seas, and ſtood as a ſure Irone poſt in the defence and ſafe conduct of the wicked Barron hir profeſſed friend, by art of wordes winding the Kinges mind to her ready bent bow, and with beautyfull countenance, indooting his concupicence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole dominion of England: all which, as a manifeſt trueth on a time approuedly fell out, for after that ſundrey of the Queenes friendes ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eliuered many pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full petitions for her enlargement, <hi>Caſiope</hi> ſecretly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them ſelues, taunted the King as followeth.</p>
                  <p>To what ſolletary wildernes is the ripenes of your pollecy wandred? Shall euery bace Subiect, hauing aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome promoſion, rather of your goodnes, then their owne deſartes, chaung your inclination as they liſt? For ſhame my Lord, put on a princely mind, put off this bace relenting hart: let Subiectes penetrate your minds not as they luſt, but as you pleaſe: let them euermore ſeeke, and neuer finde the ſecret depth of your hart: let them rather grate vpon hard Irone, then ſoft melting waxe: my counſell herein followed, and put in practiſe, will bring ſpeaciall welfare to your ſtate, and worthy eſtimation to all thoſe which attende your perſon. Further, if Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> be the pleaſant flower that euery one ſeeketh to ſmell at, doe but vnroote the ſtalke, and all their delightes will periſh. And to conclude, her life will be your death,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:17"/>and my diſhonour.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> harkening ſtill to the voyce of this night Rauen, which dayly crooked for the ſweetlife of the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene, and ſpent much commumcation with the King, as well for her diſpatchance after her deliuerance from childbirth, as conuaying the ſtate of the Kingdome to her isſhue. The which pricks and darts of mortall ſhot throwne out, ſo inwardly greeued the Lordes of the priuy Counſell, that they departed the Kinges court, reſigned their offices and rich fees, and ſould their Patrimonies: ſo that the Kingdome and dominion of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> which before abounded in proſperous felicitie, with manyfould orniaments of honour, was now ruinated with great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, wretchedneſſe and miſerie. The King neglected the care of his people: the people on the other ſide, enuied the perſon of the King &amp; their martchandize and trafficke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, their huſbandry foreſlowed, ground became barron with out tillage, &amp; miſerable famine ouer ſpred the whole Countrey: the which conſumed breede of cattle. The gold, ſiluer, and treaſures, was incroached among the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt ſubiectes, who for their better ſaffety, betooke both themſelues &amp; their riches vnder forraine gouernmentes.</p>
                  <p>Preſently vppon this hurlie burlie, which happened throughout the whole dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the heauens ſent this good fortune to Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> that in the Lord high Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals houſe, ſhe was deliuered in childbirth of two Twins, a Sonne and a Daughter, being two children of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent beauty, which by the Marſhall was preſented to King <hi>Edward:</hi> who although vtterly deſpiſing the Mother, yet not altogeather choaked in ill nature toward the infantes, ſpeedely celebrated a ſoliemne Chriſtoning, and cauſed the man child to be called <hi>Edmond,</hi> and the woman child by the name of <hi>Siluia:</hi> the which being performed by officiall
<pb facs="tcp:6036:18"/>Prieſtes, as the manner was in thoſe dayes, but yet not in ſuch a royall ſort as Princes childred ought to haue been chriſtoned: the which being no ſooner finiſhed, but the King (kindled in fuery againſt the Infantes, through the perſwaſion of fayre <hi>Caſiope</hi>) cauſed young <hi>Edmond</hi> to be conuayed into the Dukedome of <hi>Normandy:</hi> in which dominion the young Infant in company of his <hi>Engliſh</hi> nurſes was moſt honourably receiued, both becauſe that Duke <hi>Robert</hi> (being the firſt of that name) was vniſſued, as being a Kings child of royal blood, thinking that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant being naturally brought vp, would proue in time, to be a louing Prince to his people, and a careful gouernour amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>Further, King <hi>Edward</hi> in the diſpoyle of lawfull poſterety from his dominion and Kingdome, likewiſe tranſported fayre <hi>Siluia</hi> with her <hi>Engliſh</hi> nurſes into <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> where very honourable intertaynement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort was giuen in the Kinges Court, who through age and time gayned woonderfull eſtimation: for as nature had rewarded her with excellent beauty, ſo fortune forgot not to repleniſh her with wealthy proſperety, who from her childhood in Princely orniamentes proued the only Parra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon of <hi>Denmarke:</hi> where now we will leaue her for a time to her good fortunes: and likewiſe Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> in the Court of <hi>Normandie,</hi> and diſcourſe of the miſeries that happened to Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> after her deliuery of childbirth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:6036:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ How Queene Katherine was deliuered from priſon by the pollecy of the Earle of London, being her owne brother: and what happened to the Lord Marſhall after her departure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ing <hi>Edward</hi> not ending his Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fuery in the banniſhment firſt of the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> the young infant <hi>Edmond</hi> his ligitimate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, and fayre <hi>Siluia</hi> his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall daughter, but with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter determination of miſcheife, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſent letters to the high Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, giuing him a ſpetiall charge for the Queenes beheading, proteſting by the ſame let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, what peace and tranquillety thereby might be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed to his countrey.</p>
               <p>After receipt of theſe newes, the night before her death anpoynted, Lord Marſhall entered the Queenes lodging, and made relation of his charge giuen by the King for her execution: to whom ſhe with a ſober countenance anſwered in this manner. My Lord Marſhall (ſayd the Queene) be not amazed, but accompliſh your duty herein: nor thinke me diſpleaſed either with theſe newes from my deare huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, or with you the meſſenger: for I am fully reſolued that my death more greeueth you, then my ſelfe: and as you
<pb facs="tcp:6036:19"/>haue been euer carefull in my cauſe, ſo it is no little ſorrow vnto your heart I know, in that my blood thorow your handes muſt be imbrued: but this is the day which long I haue looked for, the which being now come, I greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce that my miſeries muſt be finiſhed, and the time of my ſorrowes expired: But yet a further comfort relieueth my afflicted minde, in that young <hi>Edmond</hi> my Sonne, is tranſported into the handes of the <hi>Normaine</hi> Duke, and my deare daughter <hi>Siluia,</hi> brought vp in the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markes</hi> Court, a Prince of ſingular vertue and honourable fame: their cauſes being thus ſolicited by ſtraungers, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of vnknowne men, the vigilant eye of fortune cannot choſe but be euermore caſt vpon them. And now for you my Lord Marſhall, I can but giue thankes for all curtedes and aſſuered friendſhippes, approuedly ſhewed to me in theſe my heauy woes: good my Lord, to morrow in the morning, when death haſtneth vpon me by the execution of your office, departing and ſhaking handes with this life, let it not be tedious or ouerſmartſome vnto me, but rid me quickly from my miferies.</p>
               <p>The Lord Marſhall, and the vertuous Lady his wife being as then preſent with the Queene, bathing their cheekes with floodes of teares, ſpake to her, and ſayd in theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>If that power were in vs (fayre Princeſſe) your death ſhould be deferred vntill the appoyntment of the mightie powers, whoſe leaſure your enemies ſhould waight vpon: but we fearing the vnhappy ſucceſſe and heauy burthen thereof would lodge vppon our backes, and incurre the Kinges tyranicall fury and wrath. No, no, my deare hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable friendes (replyed the Queene) I do ioyfully proſtrate my lyfe to death: Why ſhould I hope after lyfe, ſith my Lord and King deſireth my diſpatchance? If any ſuch acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:6036:19"/>take place, you my keepers ſhall taſte the ſower, and feele the ſmart thereof. If I eſcape, ſome vniuſt lot will fall vpon you: if my lyfe through your good meanes ſhould be ſaued, my enemies would fleſh them ſelues vpon you in contempt. Nay noble Queene (ſayd the Lord Marſhall) we are not affrayd to aduiſe our ſelues in defence of your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but ſhall in time to come rid and diſpatch theſe bloody varlets from the booſome of this land, which now is made vnhappy by their curſed flatterie. All which could nothing chaung her vertuous intent, but was readely prepared in minde to ſcale the immortall throwne of heauen. Her wroungfull impriſonment, the falſe accuſations layde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt her, the vnchaſt lyfe of the King hir huſband, the infinite cares which ſhe was wel acquainted with: al which gaue full inſtruction, and perſwaded her ſoule to prepare for a heauenly pilgrimage.</p>
               <p>Oh (ſayd the ſorrowfull Queene) this lyfe is a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of woe, I do abandon my whole reputation, honours, children, friends, and worldly eſtimation, as fading ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes. Oh ſayd ſhe, my enemies hath charged me with adultry, but the Gods know me a blameles innocent, as yet neuer ſtaynd with the purple ſpot of infamie.</p>
               <p>The high Marſhall and his wife paſſing all the whole night in theſe &amp; ſuch like vertuous ſpeaches, addreſſing and framing her minde to the euerlaſting voiage, where ſhe purpoſed to reſt her vnſpotted conſience, and to weare the celeſtial crowne of peace, prepared for all ſuch chaſt Ladies wrongfully accuſed.</p>
               <p>But now ſpeake we againe, of the wicked Barron of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who early in the morning came with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie band of warlike Souldiers, appoynted to execute the Kinges commaundement, beſetting the Lord Marſhals houſe round about, leaſt the condemned Queene ſhould be
<pb facs="tcp:6036:20"/>reſchewed from death: and being thus placed in the ſtreets, the Earle of London being the Queenes owne brother, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſertayne other Gentlemen of worth: all which attired in Friers garmentes, craued liſence of the common Souldiers, to goe and talke with the Queene, touching the eſtate of her conſcience, belonging to their function and calling, that through their good Counſell, ſhe might at the houre of death be well aduiſed, leſt either van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed with impenitencie, or throwne downe into deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, another lyfe ſhould be tedious and full of torments.</p>
               <p>Theſe good cauſes earneſtly conſidered by the Barron and his Souldiers, obtayned them a free recourſe to the condemned Queene, whom they preſently chaunged from Princely orniaments into a Friars weede, and ſo concucted her through the whole garriſon of Souldiers without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or ſuſpition: and being in this ſecret and diſguy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed maner tranſported to the end of the towne, the Earle of London had there prepared a Wagon, which ſpeedely caryed her onely in his company far from the daunger of their enemies. This renowned poſſecie do I repute for a vertuous deede, in deliuering the guiltleſſe Queene from the handes of ſuch tyrants: an action worthy to be regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the golden booke of fame, to ſhine as a mirrour to all enſuing ages.</p>
               <p>Shortly after the Queenes departure, thus ſuccoured by her beloued brother, the wicked Barron called at the Marſhals gate, commaunding him to bring foorth his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, ſhewing him ſelfe as though he were greatly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſtirred vp with impaſſible choller, chaſing and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as though he would teare her in peeces him ſelfe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. What, doe you daſlie with the Kinges commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Or, doth it grieue her to leaue this tranſitorie world? Is this the patient Queene, which with her faigned holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6036:20"/>hath ſo craftely crept into the fauour of the common people? Bid her not feare to hoyſt vp ſayle towardes heauen, hauing a merrie winde: bid her beholde how An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and celeſtiall troupes ſtande here attending, ſafely to conduct her to the Gods them ſelues.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſpightfull tauntes giuen againſt the Queene, bred ſuch a furie in the Lord Marſhals wife, that ſhe could not withhold her anger any longer, but deſperatly ſtept foorth, and reuiled the Barron in this maner, ſaying. Oh thou incarnate Diuell (quoth ſhe) art not thou content to wreake thy villanous minde by wrongfull accuſation againſt the good Queene, but thus rediculouſly to abuſe her miſeries? (She vttered a thouſand ſuch diſpightful words, inforced with deadly furie and fierie choller, after the ſimple ſexe of woman kinde, as if it had conſiſted in her power to haue puniſhed the Barron: ſhe yeelded ſo much to wrathful deſires, that no law could haue tamed her tongue, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned the rage of her irefull indiſcretion:) Goe ſeeke the gileleſſe Queene (ſayth ſhe) it is vnknowne to my Lord and huſband where, and to what place ſhe hath attayned. I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſuppoſe that ſhe is gon downe into the bottomleſſe pit of hell, to ſeeke ſuch a wicked varlet as thou art: for in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I know ſhe can not finde thee foorth.</p>
               <p>Well (ſayth the Barron) bring her foorth according to the ſentence of iudgement, or els the ſmart will fall vpon your ſhoulders, as well for violating the lawes of our land, as contenming the Kings will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe wordes, certaine of his moſt truſtieſt Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers violently ruſhed into the Lord Marſhals houſe, and with diligent view left no corner vnſearched: and at laſt perceiuing it a manifeſt trueth, that the Queene was ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conueyed away, they brought preſent word backe to the Barron: who in a rigorous boldneſſe, cauſed a bloody
<pb facs="tcp:6036:21"/>purſute preſently to be made: when the Lord Marſhall, his wife, children, and femelie, were put to ſharpe dint of ſworde, and hot broyles of conſuming fire, ſaue onely one of his chyldren, a proper faire virgin, being as then abſent from her father and mother, brought vp with the Earle of <hi>London,</hi> the Queenes owne brother; who after, was tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in all honourable education by Queene <hi>Katherine:</hi> whom we will leaue trauelling like baniſhed exiles, from their natiue Countrey.</p>
               <p>The Barron after this murtherſome conflict, returned ſafe to King <hi>Edwardes</hi> preſence: who not onely rewarded his valiant ſeruice with gold and rich treaſures, but inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed him with great laudes and reuenewes: and beſides all which, by letter of Deputation, he conſtituted him to guide and gouerne his whole dominions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> ¶ How King Edwardes Concubine the faire Caſiope, was deliuered of a baſtard Sonne: and of the ſecret fauours betweene her and the Barron.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE King after all theſe things were fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (as you heard diſcourſed in the former Chapter) promiſed ſecurety to him ſelfe, princely renowne to his minion <hi>Caſiope,</hi> and royal aduancement to his truſtie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour the Barron of <hi>Buckingham:</hi> yet the loue of Subiectes, a guiltles conſcience, and a good
<pb facs="tcp:6036:21"/>name (being the chiefe groundworkes of peace) were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: beſides which, the King vtterly deceyued in his owne imaginations, for that penall ſhame began euery hower to knocke at his gates, ſtayning his glory with iufamie and diſhonour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſiope</hi> his amorous Lady, being great with childe, the which ſhame, heauen had appoynted for the common ſort of people continually to talke vpon: beſides which, the Kinges vile affection poſſeſſed with leawd luſt, neuer glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but dayly ſhyning in the ſea of vaine delectations, <hi>Caſiope</hi> on her behalfe, with prouident diſcretion preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſodaine downefall: for, perceiuing the Kinges head toſſed with inconſtant inclinations, his treadinges looſe and vnſure (on whom ſhe principally depended) ſhe iudged that ſhe could not be ſo ſafely imbarked as her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation deſired, and therefore dayly wiſhed that ſhe had ended well, where ſhe had ſo ill begun.</p>
               <p>Thus tottering vpon a broken bridge, by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle caſt her ſelfe into the loue and good liking of the Barron, who vſed many ſecret contemplations, feeding each other with artificiall fauours, as opportunitie happely miniſtred occaſion, and miſſpent no one hower in the day without yeelding ſome amorous fruites.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Fdward</hi> being vtterly vnaquainted with theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtie trickes, neuer miſtruſted the cunning conueyance of <hi>Caſiopes</hi> leawd life, who paſſed foorth her time ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely without ſuſpition, vntill ſhe was deliuered: the which being fully expired, was to the King a ſecret ſolace, but an open ſhame: a priuate comfort to him ſelfe, but a publique infamie to the land, a man childe was brought foorth into the world: the which in proceſſe of time, approued the only poyſon by which the King was choaked, and a Caterpiller through whom the common wealth was gnawne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:22"/>But alas, who would regard &amp; eſteeme of an vnnaturall Baſtard, borne in a ſower crab-ſtacke, and vtterly reiect the good Children of Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> bred and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſweete Apple iuyce, which was chriſtoned in mourning and ſorrowfull teares, without any pompe and glory? Where contrary wiſe this Baſtard, the childe of a Harlot, was royally receiued into the Church, and chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the name of <hi>Vallentinus,</hi> with ſuch ſumptuous magnificence, as no King could ſurpaſſe in ſuch a caſe: for many were the triumphes, ſolemne iuſtes, and coſtly banquetings that were kept in the Engliſh Court in the honour of his name: the which for breueties ſake, I here paſſe ouer, leaſt I ſhould be a hinderaunce to our following diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>No ſmall conſolation tooke King <hi>Edward</hi> in the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and bringing vp of this filthy young venimous ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Vallentinus,</hi> who being dazeled in dotage, immagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned winter ſtormes ouerpaſt, and the pleaſant ariuall of a faire ſommer to be at hand: yet was he nipt and attached with a priuie diſeaſe in his browes, by meanes of the new enioyned loue of the Barron and <hi>Caſiope:</hi> whoſe league of friendſhyp, and falſhood of flatterie, ſo blinded the Kings conceites, that no miſtruſtfulneſſe of their lewde ſportes could ariſe. Firſt, ſweetning his mouth with the braue beautie of <hi>Caſiope.</hi> Secondly, reioyceing in the pollecie of the Barron. And thirdly, allured with the hope and bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding foorth of the baſtardly bloſſome <hi>Vallentinus:</hi> the which I compare to three broken Staues, whereon the King tooke his chiefeſt hold.</p>
               <p>What a long relation could I make of the ſport and dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance begunne betweene the wicked Barron and proude <hi>Caſiope,</hi> hauing bended the King to their bow, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the whole dominion, and contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wlyng what ſo euer
<pb facs="tcp:6036:22"/>ſeemed beſt to them ſelues. And whereas in the dayes of vertuous Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> the Kinges head was diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and fraughted with the rhewme of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elouſie, ſo now his Darling, &amp; cunning Counceller, gaue him a greater gliſter beneath, for his headaking Kerchife aboue: for ſhe yeelded her body &amp; loue to the Barrons pleaſure. When the King was ſleeping, they would be waking: when the King was in his Chamber, they were handling prettie toyes in the Cloſſet: when the King was in one place, they were in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, keeping company togither, diſcourſing vpon louers lawes. In which pleaſure, we will leaue them ſolacing, and returne to Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> and her brother the Earle of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> ¶ Of Queene Katherines ariuall in Normandie, and of her entertainment in Duke Roberts Court.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Queene (by the pollecie of her brother) had eſcaped the furious intended tyrranie of her foes, accompanied with the Lord Marſhalles Daughter tending and waighting vpon the Queenes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with great care and indeuour tooke Shippe, hauing a merrie winde, hoyſted vp ſayle towardes <hi>Normandie:</hi> into which countrey, her young ſonne Prince <hi>Edmond,</hi> was before conueyed and ariued. The tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6036:23"/>of this iourney was not ſo much troubleſome, as the dangerous daſhing vpon craggie Rockes hazarded their liues: but yet Fortune in the middle of their miſeries fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring them, caſt them happely vpon a fruitefull Iland bordering vpon the confines of <hi>Normandie:</hi> in which place a right noble Knight inhabited, gouerning the people with great wiſedome: into whoſe preſence being no ſooner come, but the Earle of <hi>London,</hi> in the name of the Queene and Lord Marſhals daughter, ſpake to the Knight as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>Moſt worthy man (ſayd he) we being ſtrangers to thy people and Iland, by vnhappy miſaduentures are compelled hither to make our refuge, and to ſeeke friendſhyp among you: for I am to let you vnderſtande, that here is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe fame (I know) hath full often ſounded in your eares: the which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Queene, long vexed with captiuitie, arraigned, and condemned to die, but yet (by good fortune) eſcaping the ſubtile ſnares of her enemies, hath betooke her ſelfe to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: and now hardly auoyding ſhypwracke, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her ſelfe to your mercie. She hath not left her natiue ſoyle for any euill deſart, leawd behauiour, or miſgouerning her lyfe, for ſhe is a continent and chaſt Matron, bearing the glory of vertue in her countenance: but yet a cruell and vniuſt woe chaunced vnto her young dayes, to become the nuptiall Spouſe of a voluptuous vnchaſt King, who more eſteemed the falſe deſembling face of a Harlot, then the chaſt beautie of this vertuous Queene: and yeelded more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite to the vniuſt accuſation of a flattering Peere, then to the pittifull teares of this honourable Perſon: whoſe lyfe from her infancie hath hitherto continued without blemiſh: Therefore now we hope, that mercy waighteth in the gates of the righteous, euer to relieue the diſtreſſed trauellers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:23"/>This being ſayd, the Knight hauing a good lyking to the bright honour which vertuouſly appeared in their faces, vouchſafed to giue them a fauorable entertainement: and according to the worthines of honourable ſtrangers, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiued them with great kindnes: who not refuſing his willing offer, with great humilitie thanked his curteſie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming themſelues in aduerſitie, as pilgrimes throwne vppon ſtrange rocks of hard fortune, were exceeding glad of friends and friendſhip.</p>
               <p>This bountifull Knight more to honour their eſtates, commanded the beſt and wealthieſt ſubiectes within the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to attend their perſons, and to prouide all neceſſaries for their needfull want: beſides which, the moſt pleſanteſt buildings within the Iland were appointed for their lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings: who after long recreation, refreſhing their wearie miſeries with good eaſe, they craued libertie to depart.</p>
               <p>But at the time of their abode in the Iland, the Knight was grieued with a moſt ſtrange diſeaſe, the which moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly tormented him through all the parts of his body: but Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> taking a view of the ſame, ſaide vnto him in theſe words. Your diſeaſe good Sir, is euidentlie knowne vnto me, being already partly acquainted with the nature therof. I am no profeſſed Phiſition, nor Chirurgion: but yet if it ſtand with your good pleaſure to aduenture your ſelfe vppon my ſimple ſkill, (although a ſtranger) yet will I ſhewe my vttermoſt experience in the recouery of your health.</p>
               <p>Moſt renowned Queene (replied the Knight) I can but thanke you for your curteous offered friendſhip: but if my health may bee recouered by your knowledge, I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a greater benefit from your good grace, then euer yet could bee miniſtred by any mortall creature. I haue to my great coſt and charge, intertained many good and learned
<pb facs="tcp:6036:24"/>phiſitions and chirurgions, from ſundry famous places of the world: yea men of renowned credit haue trauailed vnto me, yet hitherto I neuer could, neither by wiſdome, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, learning, policy, nor practiſe, be remedied or eaſed.</p>
               <p>But nowe ſuch was the vertue and grace of this noble Queene, that although ſhe was of royall bloud, yet the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe of the diſeaſe neither was lothſome vnto hir, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the daintineſſe which her degree might require, did cauſe her to refuſe any paines for accompliſhment of his health: but ſo ſhe applied her medicines within and without, of ſuch vertue &amp; effect, that in ſhort time the knight recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not onely his health, but liued long after a very perfect and ſound man.</p>
               <p>The knight hauing thus made a triall of the incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertue, wiſedome, learning, and modeſt chaſtertie of this noble Queene, cauſed hir renowne to bee publiſhed in many forraigne nations, and rewarded her with great trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: likewiſe, appointing a ſure ſhip, truſty Marriners, with great ſtore of prouiſion, for hir paſſage into <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:</hi> likewiſe, hee writ a letter to Duke <hi>Robert,</hi> touching hir rare and excellent orniaments of nature: yea, what a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned woman his country was like to inioy, wiſhing that his fortune had beene worthy of ſo bleſſed and good a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to haue dwelled amongſt his people. Thus this good Queene, hir deare brother, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidue of her honorable company, paſſed foorth their iourney towards <hi>Normandy;</hi> where, and into which countrey, ſhe was royally enterteined of Duke <hi>Robert,</hi> his Dutches, and principal eſtates of that nation, and receiued fauour of all other ſortes of people for hir curteous behauiour. In this country, her orniaments of ſkill, wortineſſe of vertue, and ſtudious learning, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, flowed, and abounded, whereby ſhe was able to diſpute, talke, and reaſon with the learnedſt phyſicion in the
<pb facs="tcp:6036:24"/>world: for ſhe was ſo much guided by wiſdomes lore, that many forraine princes came to reuerence her: beſides, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people full of ſundry diſeaſes, homaged to her perſon for remedy and eaſe, ſome for one grife, ſome for another: and to conclude, there is no diſeaſe which this gratious Queene tooke in hand, but hir excellent knowledge gaue health and ſoundneſſe. Oh how many Princes and great Monarks of the world were content to ſtoope (for health of body) to this worthy woman. What wonderfull trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and rich iewels were daily laide before hir, ſent from all the parts of the earth, in reſpect of hir magnificence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned ſame, and admirable credite, beeing vniuerſallie ſpread through all the dominions of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> ¶ How King Edward grew in miſliking with his faire mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and her ſecret friend the wickked Barron: and howe by their meanes he was depoſed, and conſtrained to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his natiue countrey.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE fame of Queene <hi>Katherines</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, (obtained in the Dukedome of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi>) did more depreſſe and martyr her enemies in England, then if ſhe had made a conqueſt of them with forty thouſande men of warre: the which her good ſucceſſe abroad (being fauored in a forraine nation) did not a little fret the cankered ſtomackes of her foes at home, as King
<pb facs="tcp:6036:25"/>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> her huſband, <hi>Caſiope,</hi> and the Barren of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam,</hi> which greatly repented themſelues that better fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt had not ſetled in their heades, in the preuention of ſuch miſchiefes, by the Queenes proſperous euent like to enſue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſiope</hi> inioying the lour, pleaſure, and faithful ſeruice of hir deare friende the Barron, beginneth nowe to fadome the deepeſt waters, and to blind the kinges eyes with the foggy miſtes of her deceitfull ſmiles: who as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of folly, was drawn to what purpoſe his Minion plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, firſt framed by the Barrons fraudulent deuiſes, ceaſſed not more and more to vſe their wits in the beſt manner they could to maintaine their vniuſt loues: and being in a feare, leaſt their leude lecherie ſhould come to the kings eares, the which not a little tormented their thoughts, aduiſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by priuy conſultation togither, howe they might beſt procure their owne ſafety. So by ſubtile ſcience of wit, they inueigled the King to deliuer vp the title of his gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and dominion to yong <hi>Valentinus</hi> his baſtard ſonne: all which being brought to vnhappy paſſe, <hi>Caſiope</hi> and the Barren her louer, for recreation ſake, might the more ſafer vſe their pleaſant delights in the Kinges preſence without ſuſpition, as though no blemiſh were in beautie, nor lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in loue.</p>
               <p>The King being thus depoſed, many times ſitting like a dizard, deſolately left to himſelfe, putting a by, receauing onely by the yeare ſixe thouſand crownes, and the wicked Barron appointed the lord Protector of young <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> who was brought vp according to his wiſhed deſire.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> now being diſcharged from the heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of a crowne, early in a ſummers morning (to refreſh his dulled wits) roade forth into a faire greene Forreſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking his company and traine, and prauncing his courſer ſomewhat aſide, by chance he met with a poore country pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:25"/>being a ſhe apheard by profeſſion: whom he ſaluted on this manner. Good morrow fellow (ſaide the King) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther art thou trauelling: Good ſir (anſwered the ſhepheard) I am trauelling to London about neceſſary buſineſſe. But tell me (quoth King <hi>Edward</hi>) doeſt thou know the King of this land? No by my troth (ſaid he) I knowe him not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I care if I neuer do, except his maners were better, and his wits more ſurer. What (ſaide the King) doth his manners indammage or hurt thee? No (ſaid the ſhepheard) but he hurts both himſelfe, his ſubiects, and his whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. The King being in wardly chafed hereat, could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouerne nature, or tie vp affection, to heare the poore countrey fellow reckon vp his abhominable life: but yet diſſembling a little longer, he aſked him what reportes the countrey did giue out of Lady <hi>Caſiope.</hi> Marry (ſaide the ſhepheard) ſome ſay that ſhe is a lewde Curtezan, and one that hath almoſt vndon this noble fruitful dominion, which for many hundred yeeres hath beene vertuouſly guided, now ouerthrowne by <hi>Caſiope:</hi> whoſe wicked counſell firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the baniſhment of Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> and hir chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and now hath vſurped the crowne and ſcepter to <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinus</hi> hir baſtard ſonne: beſides which, the King is vſed as a fiddle to plaie vpon: for the Barron of <hi>Buckingham</hi> day and night gathereth the choiſeſt flowers out of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſties garden: the which is no ſmall griefe to his ſubiects hearts. More would the ſhephearde haue ſpoken, had not King <hi>Edward</hi> interrupt him in this manner. Good fellowe (quoth he) knowe, that I my ſelfe am the king, charging and commaunding thee vpon paine of death, to giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at the court, there to auow and vtter at large the ſame words to <hi>Caſiope,</hi> which thou haſt here already diſcouered to me, I wil be thy ſafeguard from al barmes, and wil rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reward thy paines therein taken.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:26"/>Thus in a diſcontented humour, departed the King after his company: and being returned backe to the court, there he found the Shepheard according to his commandement giuen, who ſeemed to play his part before king <hi>Edward,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Caſiope,</hi> counterfeiting the geſture of an Iddiot, pleaſantly conceited himſelfe to expell fantaſticall imaginations from the kings braines. My Lord (ſaith the Shepheard) you haue a faire pond, repleniſhed with daintie fiſh, preſerued for your own taſte, but yet deceitfully robbed by night, by one which ſlattereth you by day. Your white Swan, ſwimming in a moſt pleaſant Riuer, preſerued by you, but is pluckt by others. Your delicate Plumb-tree, daintily kept for your owne tooth, hath hir boughs broken by a priuy practiſer: but ſuch is your liberal and franke hart (I know) that if within your garden a ſweet poſie be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſufficient ſmels left behind to refreſh your ſences, it wil be no griefe at al: for things vnſeene of the eie, is not rewed of the heart.</p>
               <p>This biting talke of the Shepheard, ſo opened the kings blind ſences, that he began to haue cleare knowledge of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiope</hi> and the Barrons violent villanies, whereby he fel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to witles fury, watching the gates while the City is on fire: and thought to ſubdue <hi>Caſiopes</hi> inclination, when he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was ſlaine before: ſo great was his griefe, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to curſe and ſweare, wiſhing himſelfe dead: and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe aboue all others, the moſt accurſed, in giuing credite to falſe Curtezans, and diſſembling Paracites.</p>
               <p>Well (ſaieth <hi>Caſiope</hi>) if my ſight and company haue glutted and pampered your affections, I pray you make ſpeedy deuoydance of me. I wil not impaire your honour. I was neuer accounted a lewde liuer, before I met with a violent leacher: and if you ſo gladly deſire to forſake my ſocietie, I muſt brooke and digeſt your hard nature in the
<pb facs="tcp:6036:26"/>ſame, as well as I may.</p>
               <p>Theſe furious ſtormes ouerpaſſed, the Barron the next night following, inticed the Sheapheard to a ſecret corner of the kings pallace, where he thruſt a ſharpe ſword through his hart, and buried the peſants carcaſſe within a ſtinking dunghill: the report whereof pierced the kings eares with extreame griefe: but ſeeing helpe preua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed not, as a man plagued in his head, &amp; diſeaſed in his browes, he vpbraided <hi>Caſiope</hi> of falſhood and ingratitude in this manner.</p>
               <p>If that wiſe and learned councell in times paſt, coulde haue reformed my wilfull follies, I had not nowe bin ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. If I had been guided by the example of the gentle Reed, bending with euery wind hither and thither, I had now like the proude ſtately Dake (ouer high in mine owne conceite) beene caſt vp by the rootes. The ſame ſhamefull ſcorne now happeneth to me, as to the ſimple Goate, who meeting with the crafty Foxe, drinking both togither in a deepe ditch, where the Foxe by faire wordes procured the Goate with his hornes to lift him vp to the high bankes: the ſimple Goate bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uing ouermuch to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Foxes faire words, performed his requeſt, and left himſelle ſtill in the ditch, not knowing how to eſcape, wiſhing that he had better conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before hand, what would follow after: ſo ſurely, if gouernement in the beginning had foreſeene the ende, I had not now beene ſubiect to your wicked, falſe, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed diſſimulations. Haue I hatred in place of friendſhip? hath familiarity brought contempt? and hath beneuolence nurſed ingratitude? I haue neglected all mens counſels, to preferre and aduance your reputations. I haue baniſhed wife and children, forſaken friendes and ſubiectes, ſtripped my ſelfe from all honors, and reſigned my crowne &amp; ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into your handes, onely to ſatiſfie your willes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in all points: yet for all this, brute beaſts, and foules
<pb facs="tcp:6036:27"/>of the ayre, in all thankfulneſſe and humanitie, excell your ſauadge natures.</p>
               <p>In this maner King <hi>Edward</hi> ſought to reobtaine the wonted fauour &amp; good lyking of <hi>Caſiope</hi> and the Barron, who keeping ſtill ſilence, in a great ſnuffe departed the Kinges Pallace to an other houſe, which they inioyed in the right of <hi>Vallentinus</hi> the Baſtard: and being there ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the Barron writ this Letter backe to the King, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Barron of Buckingams Letter ſent to King Edward.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR euill deſertes, and franticke faſhions, hath ſo highly offended your deareſt friendes, that they haue refuſed at any time hereafter, to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard credite, life, and goodes, in your behalfe: And ſince you haue forgot the right rule of honeſt life, abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſpetiall care of the Common-wealth (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences grow through your negligent ſlouthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) our purpoſe is therefore to haue it reformed: And now ſince fortune hath appoynted me an honorable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, in the right of virtuous <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>allentinus,</hi> I am readely bent to abridge and cut off your licentious minde and careleſſe lyuing: For as you haue diſpoſſeſſed your ſelfe from princely gouernement of the Realme, ſo we muſt conſtraine you either to liue as a priuate perſon, or els by baniſhment inforce you to forſake the land, whereby we may the better appeaſe homebred mutenies, repreſſe the practiſes of forraigne foes, and preuent the pollecies of
<pb facs="tcp:6036:27"/>Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> and her councellours: all which, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the eſtabliſhment of that famous young Prince <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>allentinus.</hi> And whereas you, hoping after the loue of <hi>Caſiope,</hi> whom you haue long time wrongfully abuſed, and made a poynting ſtocke for the worlde to wonder at; but now, repenting of her former amiſſe, ſhe determineth to retyer from infamie, and to match in honeſt marriage with my perſon, being the onely ſuer ſtaffe of her vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life: Therfore (to be ſhort) take this choiſe vnto your ſelfe, either to depart quietly into ſome forraigne region, or elſe to liue a priuate life in your owne countrey, not once comming within the ſight of our royall Court: Therefore if wiſdome may rightly perſwade you, I do not then doubt, but that you will accept that good ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way, which ſhall bring you the beſt ſecuritie: I end.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>By me the Lord Protector of the young Prince <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>allentinus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>AFter King <hi>Edward</hi> had peruſed theſe ſawcy and mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert letters, he ſtayed and breathed vpon the Barrons former flatterie: and ſeeing this ſuddaine change of louers, he often times ſighed, remembring in what ouerſight hee was led &amp; allured, iniuriouſly defaming and baniſhing his deare beloued Queene, cruelly murthering the Lord high Marſhall, his wife and children, and himſelfe vtterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiled, ouer much truſting to the trifling pleaſures of an harlot, and leaning too much to the falſe allurements of a traiterous flatterer: thorough whoſe wicked perſwaſions hee ſent his naturall children to the aduentures of rouing fortune: ſo alſo hauing reſigned the keyes of his kingdome to a baſtardly miſcreant, the ſonne of a wicked ſtrumpet: all which did not ſo much grieue his tormented mind, as in that
<pb facs="tcp:6036:28"/>he was made a ieſting ſtocke to the world, degenerated from ioyall bloud: ſuch was his diſtreſſe, that his Noble-men, graue Councellers, and valiant Captains forſooke him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him to his miſery; and his poore and needie Subiectes tried out for due vengeance vpon him.</p>
               <p>Thus finding no conſolation in his extremity, hee thus conferred with himſelfe. Oh (ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi>) if I ſtay within the territories of my kingdome, euerie man will ſcorne my wretched plight: of whom (with reaſonable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts) it may neither craue mercy nor ſuccour, hauing ſo vniuſtly wronged my countrey with an euerlaſting plague: beſides that, my mified life is offenſiue, odious, and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the company of men. Howe may I expect ſafety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my countrimen, being a King of royal bloud, turned from my gouernment, bereft from dignities, honour and renowne, and forced to take a ſtipend of ſixe thouſande crownes towards my maintenance, payde by the diſcretion of flattering traytors?</p>
               <p>The King vpon theſe inwarde piercing ſorrowes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted his dominion and natiue countrey, and without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany like a Pilgrime, wandered to what place fortune had appointed, and his own follies deſerued: ſo trauelling ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daies through ſtrange countries, it was his chance to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue in the Dukedome of <hi>Brouſwick,</hi> where being deſtitute of money, he was forced to ſell all the rings, chaines, iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s and other orniaments of gold, whereby in a ſhort time he conſumed all that hee had, and was compelled through penury and want, to craue the good will of well diſpoſed people: but euery one beholding his gallant coate vpon his backe his coſtly hat vpon his head, and his embrodered hoſe vpon his legs, eſteemed him ſome ſtout runnagate, which more delighted in wandering wildneſſe, then in good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: or, one that was ſent abroad as a Spye, to view the
<pb facs="tcp:6036:28"/>commodities of their lande and countrey, and therefore would no man extende friendſhip nor reliefe towarde his comfort.</p>
               <p>Being thus a pretty while pinched with hunger and want, and conſideting that his iuſt plague happened through the deſerts of his former life, he thought with himſelfe what good way might be beſt taken in ſo extreame a miſery; either with ſhame to make knowne what hee was, or elſe to liue in hope of ſome better chance in time to come: and being in a ſtrange countrey, he was the leſſe aſhamed of his foule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: and farre from acquaintance, his calamities became the more hardoned.</p>
               <p>So early in a morning trauelling on his way, in hope of a batter recouery, he met by chance with an old poore wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched beggar, hauing a ſimple patcht cloake vpon his backe, the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king deſired to exchange for his coſtly veſtures: a couenant betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both quickly concluded, &amp; being both contented, they ſtripped themſelues to their naked ſkinnes: the King putting on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beggars poore patched orniaments, and contrariwiſe the poore beggar addreſſing himſelfe in the Kings coſtly apparell, and ſo departed one from the other, without any further conference. Thus after leaue beeing taken, the King in his ſimple weedes laied him downe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the greene graſſe, he opened the beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars budget or ſcrip, and found ſuch good ſtore of browne breade, hard cheeſe, and bacon, that he very well relieued his terrible hunger: after which good banquet, he aroſe vp &amp; went vnto a cleere ſpring neere adioyning, &amp; drunke ſuch an inſatiable drought as though it had beene ſome Horſe or Muſe after dry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uender.</p>
               <p>Thus after King <hi>Edward</hi> had well refreſhed his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſatiſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed his greedy guts, almoſt clunged together for lacke of foode and ſuſtenance, he paſſed further into the
<pb facs="tcp:6036:29"/>countrey, continuing ſtill this courſe of life, and trauelling from place to place, he was at laſt, according to the ſtraight lawes of that countrey, apprehended and taken for a vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant runnagate: where, beeing brought before the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, he was impriſoned, whipped, &amp; rigorouſly puniſhed.</p>
               <p>About ſome two months after theſe ſharpe conſlicts, and grieuous puniſhments, a vertuous gentleman of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, reſorting by chance vnto the common priſon, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the wretched eſtate of miſerable Captiues, hee by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune caſt his eye vpon the King, which as then lay faſt fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in chaines, of whom he demanded what countrey man he was? who anſwered, that he was an Engliſh man borne, impriſoned neither for treaſon, murther, nor theft, but only becauſe he being a ſtranger, was inforced to craue reliefe of well diſpoſed people.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman perceiuing King <hi>Edward</hi> well qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in learning, and ſeeming to bee ready and perfect in the Latine and Greeke tongues, he was content to obtaine his inlargement, and freely to ſet him at liberty, if hee within his houſe would become a Schoolemaiſter for the bringing vp of his children.</p>
               <p>The King being ioyfull of this offer, and hoping after ſome better daies, he yeelded to the Gentlemans requeſt: where, after long ſeruice in the trade of a Schoolemaiſter, ſo painefully imploying his diligence to the profit of his ſchollers, that he obtained the well liking, &amp; high fauour of his Maiſter &amp; Miſtris, and was loued of the whole family: and in continuance of time, by theſe good occaſions offered, he made open confeſſion to his maiſter, that he was the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all King of England; the which being vnderſtoode by the Gentleman, forthwith (as much as his ability would ſerue) he ſafely conueied him in comely apparell, iewels, money, and other prouiſion to his daughter <hi>Siluia,</hi> brought vp as
<pb facs="tcp:6036:29"/>then in the <hi>Denmarke</hi> Court: vpon whoſe arriuall there, newes was ſent vnto the King, that a ſtranger being an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> by birth, was deſirous to ſpeake with his Maieſtie: who being full of friendly entertainement, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him in a moſt royall maner: and being come before his preſence, King <hi>Edward</hi> ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>The tempeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of aduerſitie (right excellent King) hath brought me vnto your preſence, not in any euill pretence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your countrey, but as one trayterouſly deceiued by ambitious Subiectes. For, know (moſt noble Prince) that I am the vnhappie King of <hi>England,</hi> baniſhed from my countreys and dominions, and bereft from Princely tytles, honour, and renowne: And now, ſith my deare Daughter and childe, faire <hi>Siluia,</hi> here at your coſt &amp; charge is brought vp, nature and affection haue drawne me hither to ſee her. This being ſayd, the <hi>Denmarke</hi> King with right good grace reioyced, and both courteouſly receiued and reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, profering him friendſhyp, power, and aſſiſtance, as well to maintaine his preſent eſtate, as to reſtore him againe vnto his Kingdome. Faire <hi>Siluia</hi> with great obedience, preſented her ſelfe before King <hi>Edward</hi> her father; who greatly commended her beautie, and diuine gyftes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, condemning his owne hard hart, in banyſhing her ſo vnnaturally from her natiue Countrey: for I wiſh (ſayd he) my graue had ſwallowed me aliue, when firſt my mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious minde committed her to baniſhment. Therefore in requitall of that iniurie, faire <hi>Siluia,</hi> yf euer I recouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne my right, refuſe not to be crowned the royall Queene of <hi>England.</hi> Theſe, and many more lyke ſpeaches paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rwixt King <hi>Edward</hi> and his daughter, duering the tyme of his aboade in the <hi>Denmarke</hi> Court: the which King, gaue him ſuch honorable mayntenance, as belonged to his prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtate: the rather, becauſe he eſteemed faire <hi>Siluia</hi> a meete
<pb facs="tcp:6036:30"/>wife for his ſonne and heire young <hi>Eſſricke,</hi> both being of an equall age, and nurſed vp together.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Denmarke</hi> King reuiued with a gladſome hope of climbing the higheſt top of theſe famous dignities, did make no ſpare of coſt for the accompliſhing of his haughtie expectation. Alſo, King <hi>Edward</hi> made a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined purpoſe with more deliberation &amp; riper iudgement, to reobtaine his dominion and gouernment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> ¶ How <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>allentinus the baſtard was crowned King, and how he through the perſwaſions of Perce of Winchester, cauſed his owne Mother with her paramour the wicked Barron, to be moſt ſtrangely put to death.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW muſt we ſpeake againe of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that happened in <hi>England</hi> after the Kinges baniſhment, where the wicked Barron and his minion <hi>Caſiope,</hi> many a day practiſed their wits, not onely for euer to bar king <hi>Edward</hi> from his kingdome, but vſed diligent watch, and examined the bottome of euery attempt that might practiſe his returne: but at laſt, they concluded vpon the coronation of young <hi>Vallentinus,</hi> and reſigned the Crowne and Scepter into his handes, which before time they had reſerued to his vſe, for declaration of true obedience. Many of the beſt Subiectes did ſweare diſloyaltie to King <hi>Edward,</hi> and ſubiection to the Baſtard: who had no ſooner falſely vſurpt the Crowne, but by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind behauiour, he altered the minds of the welthieſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:30"/>who in ſecuritie of their lyues, forſooke their natiue Countries, whereby the Realme was left vnpeopled, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tillage, deſtitute of bread, bereft of money, treaſures, and trafficke of marchandize from other dominions: for, their neceſſary trades decayed, and all things grew out of frame and good order.</p>
               <p>But now <hi>Vallentinus</hi> the Baſtard, beginning to grow proud, ryetous, and wanton, diſdayned the wonted checkes, of the Barron and his Mother, who many times ſought to controwle his wretchles lyfe, through which a great miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and diſſention grew amongſt them: and to make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie the more riper, there was one <hi>Sir Perce of Wincheſter,</hi> a notable cunning youth, brought vp with <hi>Vallentinus,</hi> and wholly of his counſell, who knowing him to be no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince, but a vſurper: alſo viewing the wofull cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and ruine the Countrey was brought into, ſtirred ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders more hotter amongſt them: for he ſo flattered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> young King, feeding his humors, and aduiſed him to reiect the Barron and <hi>Caſiope</hi> his Mother, to make denyall of their checkes, contemne their controulments, and to beare ſway of his owne abſolute authority.</p>
               <p>Thus being incenſed by <hi>Sir Perce,</hi> he began to rouſe vp his peacocks fethers, and to beare a malitious hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Barron and his mother, his beſt friendes and chiefe aduauncers. <hi>Sir Perce</hi> nothing fayling in all maner of deceites, playde likewiſe on the other ſide, and vnder the colour of loue that he bore to the young Prince, he wiſhed and exhorted them ſharpely to reproue the vnbridled lyfe of <hi>Vallentinus.</hi> Thus ambodexter like, this young flatterer <hi>Sir Perce of Wincheſter,</hi> vnder a cloake of true loue, ſtill feeding the ſtubborne and vnciuill natures of both parties, planted vp moſt waightie cannons, and battered the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt walles of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:31"/>
                  <hi>Caſiope</hi> and the Barron, thinking themſelues without hope of reclayming <hi>Vallentinus,</hi> ſecretly departed his Court, and rayſed vp an armie of well approued Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and attempted as well to ranſacke his Pallace, as the apprehention of his perſon. <hi>Vallentinus</hi> (through the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Sir Perce</hi>) was admoniſhed of this deuice and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and muſtred into his ſeruice the moſt couragious and valient Captaines, and beſt approued Souldiers that could be found. But now the Barron with his Armie ſeeking to preuent them, fought ſuch an vnlucky Battayle, that two thouſand of his braueſt followers came to foyle and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and him ſelfe and <hi>Caſiope</hi> taken priſoners: who by the furious crueltie of the young Prince, was clapt vp in priſon, to abide a hard and mercileſſe captiuitie.</p>
               <p>Hauing thus taken an occaſion of the time and fortune, he conſulted with <hi>Sir Perce</hi> what was beſt to be done in ſuch a buſineſſe: who hauing a wylie wit, and a craftie ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſetie, whiſpered priuely in the Princes eares, and aduiſed him to iudge them to a ſpeedy execution: for doubt you not, (quoth he) but there is iuſt cauſes to be layd agaynſt them: as chiefly your mothers filthy adulterous lyfe with that bace and wicked Barron, whoſe trayterous minde hath not onely mooued this rebellion, but hath been the cauſe of your deare fathers baniſhment: And beeing now in ſafe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, let no good fortune be neglected, till you haue expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the duetie of a louing childe, by their diſpatchance out of this tranſitorie worlde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vallentinus</hi> now wholly faſtning his minde more vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon prodigalitie, ambition, and vaine glory, then publike profite to his Crowne and Countrey, and was ignorant what danger would enſue in cutting off the Barron and his Mother, beeing his beſt friendes, and ſureſt proppes in all extremeties: therefore without any further conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:31"/>he erected, furniſhed, and ſumptuouſly builded a ſtrong Tower, very ſplendant and admirable to behold, of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull largeneſſe, deapth, and hight. He alſo cauſed a Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet to be feſtened vpon the toppe thereof: the which being no ſooner finiſhed by the handy worke of cunning Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but he commaunded the Barron and his mother <hi>Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ope</hi> diſpightfully to be brought foorth, as ſcornes of the world to ieſt vpon: where, caſting his eyes to the Tower, he ſayd: You thinke time ſleepeth, or that ſiouthfulneſſe wantonly walloweth in me: no, no, although to my great coſt, yet haue I ſetled vp a ſurer ſtay to this my Realme &amp; Countrey, then euer did my predeceſſours before me: For I haue here eſtabliſhed a Tower to hange trayterous Knaues &amp; Curtizans vpon. The worlde ſhall not adiudge me partiall in my Lawes: for ſubiectes ſhall drinke alike of one cuppe and licour. This being ſayd, he cauſed the Barron and <hi>Caſiope,</hi> to be againe carryed to priſon, and there to remayne tyll his further pleaſure, euery hower ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the deadly ſtroke that ſhould ſeperate their bodyes from their ſoules.</p>
               <p>All this while <hi>Sir Perce</hi> was not vnbuſied, omitting no time that might further his intent, but continually fillyng <hi>Vallentines</hi> eares with ſtrong perſwaſions, that their liues and ſpirits might be ſpeedely depriued a ſunder: which bloudy ſtratagem was not long a finiſhyng; for the young Prince, or rather vnnaturall viper, in this maner powred downe the tempeſtious ſhowers of truell murther: for early in the mornyng, he cauſed his Mother <hi>Caſiope</hi> to be brought foorth, who the night before hauing intelligence by her keepers, that her dayes were at an ende, cloathed her ſelfe in veſtments of white ſilke: and comming before her baſtard ſonne, ſhe very humbly proſtrated her ſelfe, and craued pittie, mercie, and forgiueneſſe at his handes, and
<pb facs="tcp:6036:32"/>with a bluſhing countenance, as beautifull as the new bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Roſe, ſhe ſpake in this maner.</p>
               <p>Oh ſonne <hi>Valentinus</hi> (ſaid ſhe) remember that I am the Mother, thy ſelfe faſhioned of my wombe and body, and by nature ſpringing from the tree of my life: yet thou like a moſt vnnatural Homicide, ſeckeſt to ſhorten my daies, and to ſtop my breath, whereas thou oughteſt in duety and obedience to vpholde my honour, and prolong my life. I do confeſſe my vile offences haue deſerued puniſhment: but ſhall mine owne child be the reuenger thereof: The baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of good Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> and the confuſion of all her friends, through my vniuſt meanes was accompliſhed, with many other miſeries which I haue ouerburthened this lande withall, onely to aduance an vngratefull diſſembler, which like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Viper ſeeketh to finiſh the life of his deareſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuts. Many more were the ſpeeches which <hi>Caſiope</hi> ſpake, in hope to attract remorſe from hir Iron harted ſonne: who nothing regarded her words, but rather the more imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſtirred vp into a greater fury, by a preſent comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, he cauſed her bodie to be caſt vpon a Table, and hir hands and legs to be houlden by the ſtrength of men: the which being done, he with a ſharpe knife cut his Mothers throate: and with the ſame butcherly inſtrument deſeuered her liſly necke from hir ſhoulders, which! ad wont to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with a glittering chaine of pure gold. After this, he cauſed the place which firſt conceaued him to be ript vp, and ſild full of corny ſalt: where after hir belly being thus cloſed vp, he gaue commandement to haue her dead carcaſſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the top of the Tower, &amp; there hung vpon a Iibbet. Her deare friende the Barron, was vſed in the ſame order: for he had his mouth ſtuft ful of burning Pepper, and hung likewiſe vpon the ſame Iibbet aliue, as a iuſt view of ſuch vngeateful flatterers, and adulterous traitours to behold.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:32"/>This bloudy action being finiſhed, <hi>Valentinus</hi> ſpake to the people many reprochfull wordes in the diſgrace of the wicked Barron, and <hi>Caſiope</hi> his mother, calling her the She-deuouring Beare of England, &amp; hir deare friend, the firſt cauſer of King <hi>Edwards</hi> diſhonour: in which tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call courſe of life, our ſtory bids vs now leaue the baſtard <hi>Valentinus</hi> with his new friend <hi>Sir Perce,</hi> and ſpeake of the accidents that happened in the <hi>Normaine</hi> court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> ¶ How Prince Edmond returned againe into England, and was crowned King: and how the baſtarde King was put to death after a strange maner.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>VEENE <hi>Katherine</hi> as you heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, after her wrongfull baniſhment from England, was graciouſly entertained of the <hi>Normane</hi> Duke, where ſhe dayly had intelligence of the wofull eſtate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, by many of hir diſtreſſed countrymen which continually fled thither for ſuccour: in the redreſſe of whoſe miſeries, ſhee made ſuite vnto Duke <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Normandie,</hi> that hir young ſonne Prince <hi>Edmund</hi> might returne into Enland, not onely to poſſeſſe himſelfe into the rightfull inheritance of his owne dominions, but to repreſſe the pride of the miſcreant baſtard, whoſe tyrannize had made England the perfect merror of calamity, and the wofulleſt nation vnder the cope of heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:33"/>In this maner euery day Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> ſolicited Duke <hi>Robert</hi> with fauourable petitions for the furniſhing of her ſonne into his owne Countrey with a band of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Souldiers: vnto whom the <hi>Normane</hi> Duke anſwered in this maner. Loth I am faire Queene) that your princely ſonne ſhould forſake my dukedome and dominion, being the only ſtaffe of my old age; and after my death, the hope of my ſubiectes: although not naturally borne amongſt them, yet comming of a royall blood, the ſonne of a maieſtical Prince, they will rather ſubmit to his obedience, then to the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one of a ſimpler birth. No, no (ſayd Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi>) there is no reaſon why a ſtranger ſhould be Prince of forraigne ſubiectes, through whom they ſhould be either too much burthened, or mooued to diſdaine: and therefore (moſt noble Duke) I humbly craue, that permiſſion may be graunted for his departure: and in regarde of your princely liberality, hauing brought him vp to ſuch abilitie, proweſſe, and warlike perfection, he ſhalbe bound to confeſſe homage and loyaltie to your kingdome whilſt he liueth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Normane</hi> Duke being poſſeſt with a milde nature, and ready in all actions to ſatisfie Queene <hi>Katherines</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, preſently muſtered a great multitude as well of <hi>Normane</hi> ſouldiers, as exiled <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> which zelouſly proteſted all duetifull indeuours in the young Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and in the accompliſhment of that honorable exployte. Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> hauing gathered great maſſes of golde and ſiluer, attayned through her learned ſkill, and practiſe in Phiſicke, furniſhed her ſonne Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> with ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, that nothing wanted either to his aduenture, or contentment: and ſo beeing furniſhed with Munition, Ships, and Souldiers, he hoyſted vp ſayle, and with a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie winde, ſafely arriued vpon the confines of <hi>England:</hi> where preſently he aduanced his Culloures, and planted his
<pb facs="tcp:6036:33"/>forces to the beſt aduantage.</p>
               <p>But now the baſtard Prince <hi>Valentinus,</hi> being amazed at the ſight hereof, with a fearefull troubled minde, greatly miſdoubted that his kingly gouernment was at an ende: yet hauing muſtered vp a ſlender armie of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Souldiers, nothing auayleable for his defence, he committed them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the leading of <hi>Sir Perce of Wincheſter:</hi> who tendering his owne ſafety, went to the enemy, where both him ſelfe and his ſouldiers, ſware true obedience to Prince <hi>Edmond.</hi> This vnexpected accident ſo daunted the baſtard King, that he grew deſperate of good happe: and being left as a naked man, he ſecretly conueyed himſelfe to the Tower, and hid himſelfe in an obſcure den,</p>
               <p>Thus Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> without any further diſturbance, quietly entred the Kingdome, where he tooke vpon him the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> crowne, placing the baniſhed <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> men in honorable dignities, &amp; moſt richly aduanced the <hi>Normane</hi> ſouldiers: the which being ſo luckely accomply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, he cauſed the baſtard to be ſearched foorth, &amp; his mouth likewiſe to be ſtuffed &amp; cloſed vp with burning Pepper, and hanged aliue in chaynes of Iron by the Barron &amp; <hi>Caſiope,</hi> vpon the top of the Tower, as you heard before ſo vſed.</p>
               <p>Euery thing brought thus to ſo good a paſſe, <hi>England</hi> in ſhort time became well unpeopled againe, the Realme multiplied in gold &amp; ſiluer: noble Famelies adorned with honorable poſſeſſions: Lords, Knights, Eſquires, &amp; Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in ſemblable degree endowed: Marchantes and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers well placed for traffique from forraigne regions: great vent and tillage, and breede of cattle increaſed: learning and liberall artes maintained: Marſhall proweſſe exerciſed, and all things els in moſt decent maner placed: the which we will paſſe ouer, and ſpeake of King <hi>Edward,</hi> lyuing in the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:6036:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 11.</hi> ¶ Of the Warres betweene King Edward and his owne Sonne, and the ſucceſse thereof, with other thinges that hapned.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe affaires could not be ſo priuatly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>England,</hi> but that King <hi>Edward</hi> had intelligence thereof in <hi>Denmarke:</hi> who with a reſolute determination deſired to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into his natiue Countrey; not onely that his olde age might be there comforted, but that his daughter <hi>Siluia</hi> might be ioyned in marriage with <hi>Eſſricke</hi> the Prince of <hi>Denmarke:</hi> whoſe father, in the redreſſe of King <hi>Edwards</hi> long offlictions, cauſed the ſecond part of all his able men at armes to be muſtred vp, and prouided rich treaſures for Souldiers pay, with war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like weapons, armour, and ſtore of ſhyppes neceſſary for ſuch a dangerous exployte, and publiſhed by Proclamation through all the Prouinces of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> that king <hi>Edward</hi> was to reclaime his lawfull right in <hi>England,</hi> vniuſtly vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by his owne Sonne: with many other incouragements giuen out, to animate his Subiectes, to proceede with reſolution.</p>
               <p>This buſie preparation in <hi>Denmarke</hi> ſo pierced <hi>Sir Perce of Wincheſters</hi> eares in <hi>England,</hi> that he miſtruſted his eſtate to be dangerous, and that his doble dealing would be ſhortly eſpied: in the preuention whereof, the better to protect and defend him ſelfe, he writ this priuie Letter to King <hi>Edward,</hi> as followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6036:34"/>
                     <head>Sir Perce of Wincheſters Letter, ſent to king Edward.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OTHING ſhall intice my hart (moſt Soueraigne Lord) to prooue disloyall to your Mateſtie: nor nothing reſtraine the ſeruiceable duetie which I owe vnto your Excellence. And although I was in my cradle when firſt you left your naturall Countrey of England, but yet now being growne vp to ſufficient reaſon, do aſſemble all my powers of nature, what pollecie chiefly may preuayle, or practiſe procure your recouerie: For there is nothing that my drouping ſoule wiſheth for more, then your happy returne to your former poſſesſions. I loue Prince <hi>Edmond,</hi> if he reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence your Maieſtie; and I wiſh him good ſucceſſe, if he ſhew the duetie of a ſonne vnto his father: againſt whom if he lift but his hand in wrath, the Gods will wreake iuſt vengeance and deſtruction vpon. Therefore moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord, thinke it not danger to returne, for I will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell him to ſubmisſion, ſhewing what execrable ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is pottended to them which draw the ſworde of tyrranie againſt their owne Fathers. I will admoniſh him to conuerſe, leaſt his owne wilfull conceite bring him to perdition. Thus may I both defend and counſell him, without ſuſpition of the world: and alſo therevpon ſhew fauour and reuerence to your worthy Maieſtie.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Thus fare you well.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>THIS Letter being tranſported to King <hi>Edward</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Denmarke,</hi> was receined as ſweete flowers, with promiſed requitall, the which refreſhed his drouping ſenſes,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:35"/>and changed diſpaire into perfect aſſurance; and thinking now to recouer his former right by the meanes of <hi>Sir Perce,</hi> vpon whoſe backe the common wealth of <hi>England</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: but fearing leaſt his proffered affections ſhould alter, he ſent this anſwere to his letters, as followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>King Edwards anſwere to Sir Perce of Wincheſters Letter.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Neuer diſpaired, but the Gods, (which hitherto hath gouerned all my attemptes) would at laſt ſend ſome comfort to my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and bring me againe to the full perfection of my felicitie; which through your wiſedome and pollecie muſt be attained. Therefore, in moſt humble ſort I do accept your kind proffer; and this your loyall enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe ſhall in the higheſt degree, be blazed amongſt my beſt friendes: and vntill my ſoule be diuorſed from my body, I ſhall neuer forget the loue of ſo faythfull a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; hencefoorth vowing to put off all feminine affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vaine delightes, which haunt Princes Pallaces, and the Courtes of mightie Kinges.</p>
                     <p>Haue not I iuſt cauſe to render thankes to the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Gods, that in the middeſt of my miſeries I haue found ſo prudent and worthy a friend as is your noble ſelfe, whoſe loyall hart is wholly conſecrated to my good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. Euery day do I waſh my face with teares for the tragicall ruine of my Countrey; and euery day do I breath out ſorrowfull ſighes from the cloſure of my ſoule, to thinke how the light beames of my princely honours hath
<pb facs="tcp:6036:35"/>been darkened by the falſehood of <hi>Caſiope,</hi> and the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons cunning craft, whereby my poore Subiectes haue bin in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, and my ſelfe plundged in carefull calamities; all which, greeueth not my ſoule ſo much, as that mine owne childe now, contrary to the duetifull obedience of a Soune, doth vſurpe my Crowne, and holdeth vp the ſword of ſedition againſt his owne Father: But yet I ſee the Gods will ſtill preſerue both my lyfe and honour, in that you are appoyuted to remedy my diſtreſſe, and correct the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yterous treſpaſſe of a wicked Sonne. Thus I end, aſſuring my ſelfe, that my fortune ſhall amount to the lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie turrets of my deſire, and likwiſe tread <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>owne diſgrace, and quench the ſcorching flames of noyſome enemies: thus wiſhing you as my ſelfe, I bid you farewell.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>YET for all this, King <hi>Edward</hi> regarded this perſon but as a prodigall and climbing traytor, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly aſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after princely dignities, and therefore entertained and placed in the ranke of falſe friends, vſing him as a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and image of a dead man, without either reſpecting his valloure, or truſting to his faigned flatteries.</p>
               <p>But now in the meaue ſpace, whilſt theſe things were a working, Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> vnderſtood (by a priuate friend) of <hi>Wincheſters</hi> peſtiferous treaſons: to the reformation whereof, he ſent foorth a truſtie band of Souldiers for his apprehention: which newes by <hi>Sir Perce</hi> was firſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and therefore he fled ſecretly into <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed to King <hi>Edward</hi> all the pollecies practiſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> for which, he was richly recompenced and rewarded with ſumptuous entertainement. After whoſe departure, Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> felt the toundation of his Kingdome to begin to ſhake, and thinking now to be cloaked vnder his Mothers wing, he writeth to her of the ſtarting away of
<pb facs="tcp:6036:36"/>
                  <hi>Wincheſter</hi> his chiefe Counſeller, who hath not only ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the true duetie of a ſubiect, but impayred the ſafeguard of his regiment, and diſcloſed the priuities of his counſell.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Prince Edmonds letters to Queene Katherine, ſent to her into Normandie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EARE and welbeloued Mother, I haue ſeene, and knowne, and now at length found the force of a flatterer: for the vnconſtant knight of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> with falſe colours hath bleared my eyes; He hath ſucked honey in England, and now ſpitteth poyſon in Denmarke; he hath drawne out a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed ſword to hacke a ſunder my rule &amp; gouernment: He that was wont to comfort me with counſels, now kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth me with deadly deſtruction. Therefore my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Mother, as you did ſafely conduct me hither, ſo leaue me not now in danger of confuſion; for I am as one wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſundry extremeties, ſould into the handes of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, eyther to yeeld with repulſe and ſhame, or haue my young vnexperienced age conquered with death: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſweete Mother, ayde me with your ſtrong hand, that theſe dangers layde againſt me may be eſcaped. Rule me with reaſon, and with your honourable wiſedome counſell me, that I may euer hereafter gouerne my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with diſcretion, and neuer more be troubled with treaſons of a flatterer, whoſe villanies hencefoorth I will diſdaine, and no more regard them then the chaffe blowne away with the wind. Deare Mother, ſpeedely anſwere my diſtreſſed deſires, that my ſoule may not euer languiſh in diſtreſſe. Thus ending at this time, wiſhing the heauens to bleſſe you with honourable and long life; fare you well. From our Engliſh Court.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:36"/>WHen Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> had receiued Prince <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> Letters, ſhe in tenderneſſe of hart wept bitter teares: but yet being perfectly inſtructed in wiſedomes preceptes, thought it againſt the lawes of nature to ſtriue againſt her huſband, therefore ſhe poured foorth theſe ſage ſentenſes, the which in maner of a Letter ſhe returned backe into <hi>England</hi> to Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> her ſonne.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Queene Katherines Letters of confolation, ſent to her ſonne in England.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wel remembred (my princely Sonne) that flatterers vndermining Kingdomes, are Timber-wormes, which lurke in the ſecret celles of Princes conſciences, that counterfeites the complexions of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and filles their booſoms vp with the noble blood of honorable Houſes: Why had not you then read and turnd ouer the auncient Chronicles of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and ſeene into the fall of Princes, practiſed by the pride of flattering ſtartups? The <hi>Lacedimonian</hi> Kinges, although preſerued in walles of Iron, and in towers and caſtles of braſſe, yet by the deceite of flattering traytors, were their princely gloryes ſubuerted to miſerable infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The <hi>Grecian</hi> Princes continually placed in Chariots and cloſe Litters of golde, guarded with great armies and hoaſtes of puiſſant Souldiers; yet through the ſufferance of falſe flatterers, were they dayly diuerted to ſodaine confuſion. I ſay my deare and honorable Sonne, looke into the gouernement of our auncient Kings of England, who retaind none into their counſels, but the ſonnes of Noble families, borne to honorable giftes of nature, wiſe, vertuous, and of a ciuill gouernement: If any of a bace
<pb facs="tcp:6036:37"/>birth were entertained into Princes fauours, firſt were they tried, and then truſted: deſerued, then honored: well approued, and then credited. I ſay, if either learning, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or experience, had in any poynt ruled thee, ſweete flattery had not thus ouerreacht thee, nor ſubtill diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſo deceiued thee: and to conclud, King <hi>Edward</hi> my husband and thy father, in loue equall vnto vs both, may not be vndermined by me, nor reſiſted by thee. I may well councel, but not defend thee, nor any way miniſter comfort to thy ſorrowfull afflictions, eſpecially againſt mine owne deere husband, and thy father: and as I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh thee to reuerence his perſon, ſo I charge thee to reſtraine thy ſtubborne wil; for although he hath heaped manifold miſeries vpon my backe, yet with all honour to his perſon wil I diſcarge my ſelfe. Thus fare you well, from the Court of Normandy.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your ſorrowfull Mother, vnhappy Katherine.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> although ſhee fauoured her ſonne, yet would ſhe not ſeeke to reſiſt King <hi>Edward</hi> hir huſband, but with wiſdome, obedience, and humilitie, gaue the world to vnderſtand, what glory and magnificence adorned her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: and although motherly nature willed her to ſeek the aduancement of hir ſonne, yet diſcretion did medigate the meanes that might ſcandolize the honour of hir huſbande. Whereas Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> reſted in equall loue indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently betweene them both, ſo the Earle of <hi>London</hi> being hir brother, and Prince <hi>Edmonds</hi> Vncle, matched in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the Dutches of Brittaine, which honorable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment happened through his ſiſters credite, who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his Couſins diſtreſſe, as well by King <hi>Edwards</hi> prepared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, as <hi>Wincheſters</hi> falſe trecheries in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing
<pb facs="tcp:6036:37"/>his ſubiection, raiſed a great Armie of ſouldiers, to the number of thirtie thouſand able warriours, the which he conueyed into <hi>England</hi> to be imployed in Prince <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> ſeruice.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, the good Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> after his baniſhment fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>England,</hi> was highly graced with ſo tunes felicitie, where through his Knighthood and manly behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, he got ſuch good lyking of the Queene of <hi>Portingale,</hi> into which cruntrey he trauelled, that ſhe receiued him into her fauour, and changed his wandring life into princely eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, betrothing her loue and kingdome to his gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whilſt ſhe liued: and after her death, this noble Duke, by the generall voyce of the <hi>Portingals,</hi> was elected King and ruler in her ſtead.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> being thus crowned King of <hi>Portingale,</hi> not of compulſion, but in curteſie, requeſted ten thouſand able men to be preſt in his friend <hi>Edmonds</hi> behalf: the which multitude being leuied, and accepted into ſeruice, were conducted into <hi>England,</hi> &amp; there by Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> moſt courteouſly entertained: who being now ſtrengthened with the Duke of <hi>Suffolkes</hi> ſouldiers from <hi>Portingale,</hi> with the Earle of <hi>Londons</hi> ſouldiers from <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and with his owne ſouldiers in <hi>England,</hi> being all conueyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one mayne Battaile, he waighed in the ballance of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eyther an honourable winning of renowne, or a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all his kingly dignities.</p>
               <p>So vpon a time, aſſembling all the whole Armie of ſouldiers togither, as well <hi>Brittaines, Portingales,</hi> as <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> who to inflame their vndoubted mindes to honorable reſolution, vpon an open Theator he ſpake this Oration following.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6036:38"/>
                     <head>Prince Edmonds Oration to his Souldiers.</head>
                     <p>ALthough this our dominion of <hi>England</hi> (moſt noble Souldiers and worthy Subiectes) hath of late been made a common ſpoyle by ſundry bace flatterers, and impudent traytors, deepely digging and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining our royall eſtate: The freſhe memorie of which Engliſh miſeries, through <hi>Caſiopes</hi> filthy lyfe, the wicked Barrons cruell extortion, and the Baſtards falſe vſurpation, might eaſely from your eyes conſtraine a fountaine of teares: which greeuous calamities at length through my Mothers care was taken away, and my ſelfe being young, and without experience, ſetled among you, am now in hazard to be bereaued not onely of lyfe, but of rule and gouernement: the which if it bee vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately brought to paſſe, what other hopes may you then expect, but to bee ranſacked and diſpoyled of all your poſſeſsions and wealth: your young men put to violent ſworde, your wiues rauiſhed, and your daughters euerie one defloured: ſurely then let troth bee in your hearts, ſtirre vp your valours, manifeſt your noble minds, and ſtretch forth the power and ſtrength of men, whereby that they which ſeeke to winne our ioyes, may firſt bee drowned in a ſea of ſorrowes: and thoſe that will bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with crownes, muſt firſt in marſhal fields obtaine a victorie: therefore my louing ſouldiours, if you ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtand, I wil ſprinkle my heart bloud vpon our Engliſh ground, before that cowardize ſhall inforce me to flie, or looſe one iotte or little portion of my kingdome. Be not amazed my friends and country-men, either let vs liue to maintaine our ſtates together at liberty, or elſe looſe our liues with fame &amp; renowne. Thus much I truſt, ſufficeth to witneſſe the vnfeigned affection the which I beare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you; from whoſe loue, I wil neuer depart, till death.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6036:38"/>THis Knightly Oration, ſo reioyced the ſoldiours harts, that they almoſt willingly offered their liues a ſacrifice in Prince <hi>Edmonds</hi> ſeruice, and made choiſe rather to fight in defence of their Countrey, then to be captiuated with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall ſlauery: for whereas the Engliſh forces were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeparated in their ſeuerall opinions, ſo nowe were they with inſeparable heartes knit faſt together, valiantly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to trie the laſt euent of this dangerous warre.</p>
               <p>Thus whilſt Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> incouraged his followers in this Knightly maner, the <hi>Denmarke</hi> King, with King <hi>Edward,</hi> ariued on the coaſtes of Englande with a mightie band of armed ſouldiours, intermingled with the ayde of many forraine Princes, who marched ſucceſfully to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place in Rent, whereas they pitched their forces at the bottome of a high hill: in which place, the <hi>Daniſh</hi> King being a perfect good ſouldiour, &amp; a man of a prudent iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, practiſed many excellent pollicyes: for in the night time, he cauſed a thouſand wild horſes with hollow rattls of yron faſtened to their neckes, to be ſent forth vpon the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh tents without returne: this in-rode being ſo confuſedly entered, he ordained alſo an hoaſt of foure thouſand ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours to purſue them with wilde fire &amp; burning brimſtone in their handes. In this maner entred they vpon the Engliſh ſouldiers as naked men, and diſpoiled the whole multitude of their liues: in which conflict, Prince <hi>Edmond</hi> was taken priſoner, who had his head (by his owne fathers commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſtroken from his ſhoulders, and pitched vpon the top of a Pikes ende.</p>
               <p>The battle thus ceaſing: newes by a publike reporte was ſpread throughout the land of Prince <hi>Edmonds</hi> death: at which report the cities and principall houlds in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey were yeelded vp, and the forraine ſouldiours being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to ſhift for themſelues, eſcaped away in the night:
<pb facs="tcp:6036:39"/>after whoſe departure, King <hi>Edward</hi> although in vtter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the people, yet once againe gloriouſlie entered into his kingdome, and became their gouernour: where, after he had ſetled himſelfe, and the <hi>Denmarke</hi> King taken leaue, and departed backe into his Eountrey: but King <hi>Edwarde</hi> repoſſes ſing his former eſtate larde ſharpe puniſhments &amp; harde lawes vppon the Engliſh-mens backes, the which brought him againe into cankered contempt: for the people being vnruly, with vnbrideled will placed their former ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt him: vpon which, the King for his better fecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie reſigned his crowne and gouernement to his daughter <hi>Silina,</hi> and vnto Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> hir huſband, and ſo betooke himſelfe to priuate pleaſure and reſt.</p>
               <p>Lorde <hi>Eſſricke</hi> and faire <hi>Silura</hi> with renowned honour thus tooke vpon them the gouernment of the land, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were vnacquainted with the manners &amp; conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people, they retained Sir, <hi>Perce</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to be eſperially of their councel, and their only Secretarie, who cunningly dehaued himſelfe, that he obtained the faudr and friendſhip of the common fort, winding himſelfe more and more into their priuities in ſuch ſort, that he perſwaded the people that Lord <hi>Eſſticke</hi> and Lady <hi>Siluia</hi> were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall Princes, and vnfit to gouerne ſo ſouing a people.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Perce</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> thus got into the loue of the common ſort, winked vppon all tranſgreſſions, fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed traytors, theeues, harlots, and ſuch diſſolute perſons, and many times hauing a company of ſimple then in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, he would ſpeake to them in this maner, ſaying Oh if I were your gouernour, &amp; the awful ſword of Iuſtice in my hands, what liberty the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ouerſhadow your attions for without controuſment or puniſhment then, ſhould you freely liue, and haue both honour, wealth, &amp; pleaſure, at your will.</p>
               <p>This practiſe fecretly came to king <hi>Edwards</hi> eares, who
<pb facs="tcp:6036:39"/>being well acquainted with the driftes of flatterers, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at the memorie of his former miſeries, led <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> by faire wordes vp to the top of a high Tower, whereas ouerlooking the ſame, King <hi>Edward,</hi> with other confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, appoynted for that purpoſe, caſt him hedlong ouer the wall, daſhing his bones againſt the hard ground, &amp; ſo brake his necke: euen as he craftely crept into the fauour of the common ſort, ſo wretchedly with ſhame and diſhonour en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he his life.</p>
               <p>Now King <hi>Edward</hi> thinking the eſtate of his kingdome freed from all traitrous complotters gaue him ſelfe wholly to voluptuous deſires: and hauing vnchaſt luſt harboring in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt (againſt all nature) he deſired inceſtious concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with faire <hi>Siluia</hi> his owne daughter: and being in a ſecret chamber ready to inforce her to that filthy fact, ſhe ſpake to him in this maner.</p>
               <p>Deare Father, remember the honour of your houſe, my alcadance and duetie to my huſband, and the violating of my nuptiall chaſtetie: all which (if you commit your pretended ſinne) will bring a heauy iudgement and greeuous ſcourge from God to puniſh our wicked deed, and euermore in this worlde we ſhalbe made a diſdaine and open contempt to be gaped at. All which perſwaſions nothing preuayled, for the King being drowned in forgetfulneſſe of former miſeries, inforced vehemently the rauiſhment and deflowring of his daughter <hi>Siluiaes</hi> honorable chaſtety: the which being no ſoner obtained, and ſhamefully committed, but by the iuſt iudgement of God, he was ſodainly ſtroken with death: for in his daughters preſence, a fearefull flambe of burning fire deſcended from the celeſtiall throne of heauen, and bereaued him both of ſpeach and lyfe in a moment, in the twinckling of an eye. Which ſtrange vengeance was no litle vexation to the ſorrowfull hart of Lady <hi>Siluia;</hi> yet remembring the
<pb facs="tcp:6036:40"/>duety of a daughter to her father, ſhe cauſed a coſtly Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pure wrought gold to be framed, wherein with her huſbands conſent) he was with great honour intombed, as though he had left this tranſitorie world naturally, without any ſuch violent end.</p>
               <p>After king <hi>Edwards</hi> death thus ſtrangely happened, Lord <hi>Eſſrick</hi> vpon his owne abſolute authority bore ſway among the people, who was not able to gouerne the countrey, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were with mercileſſe tyrannie: for the natures of <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> be euermore ſuch, that they wil not indure nor ſuſtame the burthens of any forraine Prince. In the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of which rule, they did not onely diſpirſe ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous ſlaunders againſt him throughout the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but alſo trayterouſly conſpired the finall diſtruction of his life: which wilfull treacheries might haue eaſely bin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, had not Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> miſliked the ſweete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant mariage eſtate of virtuous <hi>Siluia</hi> his wife: for after hir company became loathſome to his good liking, the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could not long continue vnhazarded.</p>
               <p>Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> was not only now led with an ambitious and princely deſire, but alſo had his affections ouer maſtered with witleſſe cogitations, feruently burning with the ſtrange Iuſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ladies: and being thus vainely intended, he diſdayned the comely beauty and honorable perſonage of faire <hi>Siluia;</hi> whereby bright gold ſeemed droſſe, pure wine reputed ſtinking water: and the pleaſant flowers before ſmelling ſweetely, were now eſteemed ſtinking weedes. Thus his holſome ſenſes being corrupted with luſt, faire <hi>Siluias</hi> vertues in his eyes ſeemed nothing delightſome: ſo loathſome he accompted her preſence to his company, that he dayly practiſed a meane wherby ſhe might be diſpatched: but at laſt, after many deuiſes touching her death, he conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about the ſame with a doctor of Phiſicke, who although
<pb facs="tcp:6036:40"/>well qualletied, and ſingulerly experienced, &amp; deepely ſeene in that noble and reuerent ſcience, yet a couetous gaine, and a deſire of eſtimation (as a lewde inſtrument to any vile pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) puffed him vp, and made him conſent to the ouerthrow and fatall finiſhyng of the ſweete and tender life of Lady <hi>Siluia:</hi> who hauing receiued an earneſt of a rich rewarde from Lord <hi>Eſſricke,</hi> he prepared a fatall potion to caſt her into her euerlaſting ſleepe. The which Potion, or rather deadly Poyſon, being no ſooner miniſtred by the Phiſitian, and receiued by faire <hi>Siluia,</hi> but preſently ſhe was drowned in a deadly and vnwakefull ſleepe, wherein her vitall ſenſes were ſo mortified, that her ſweete body looſing both ſtrength and operation, yeelded vp her dellicate life without hope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ouerie. The vncertaintie of <hi>Siluias</hi> death being reported abroad, cauſed many doubtfull ſurmiſes to be made, ſome one way, ſome another of her tragicall end: but yet to ſalue this contagious ſore, Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> her huſband, by procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation publiſhed throughout the dominion of <hi>England</hi> her honorable and liberall Funerall: the which was openly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized in the cittie of London, not only to creepe into the fauours of the vulgar ſort of people, but alſo to cloake and burie the murther vp in hidden ſecrecie; by which cunning meanes he thought the more ſafer to climbe to the higheſt top of the Kingdome, without either ſtop or impedimented ſtay by any one whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>After the honorable funerall of Lady <hi>Siluia</hi> was finiſhed, and her dellicate body intombed in the grauelled earth, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Engliſh Prieſtes (by a generall ſpeach dayly giuen out by the common ſort) heard reported, that Lady <hi>Siluia</hi> was buried by her huſbandes appoyntment with great ſtore of treaſure about her: to the attayning thereof, to the number of fourtie officiall Prieſtes, in a night ſecretly attempted to digge vp the Ladyes body, thereby to inrich themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:6036:41"/>with ineſtimable ſtore of treaſure, that all their liues after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward might be ſtored with plentie of wealth. But now to put this exployet and vile enterpriſe in practiſe, in the mddle houre of the night they met all together at <hi>Silu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> Tombe, where they ſpeedely delued &amp; digged vp her ſanctified body: the which being taken vp, they perceiued their intentes to be fruſtrate; and miſſing the gaiue of that which they moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, they ſodainly departed, and lett the coarſe naked vpon the bare ground, the which ſo openly was left to be ſeene of euery one, that all the beholders might eaſely perceuie, that ſhe had her death contriued by the violence of poyſon.</p>
               <p>The body of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ia</hi> being thus priuily vntombed, preſent newes of the ſame was tranſported to he hearing of Lord <hi>Eſſricke,</hi> who fearing his vnnaturall murthering of her daintie life would be brought in publique queſtion to the worlde, therfore preſently ſending for the Phiſitian, whoſe counſell he chiefly re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uired in this cauſe, and diligently fado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the deapth thereof how Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> might beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard his owne perſon, defend his credite, and poſſeſſe the Kingdome in the honour of the people. But now ſuch was the frawdullem attempts of theſe two ſecret murtherers, by in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſition they found, that the conſpiracie &amp; treaſon in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp of <hi>Siluias</hi> body proceeded from the Engliſh Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: for which fact, moſt execrable crueitie was prepared for them: for by the worthy and diligent ſearch, and the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians pollecie, the general number of thoſe Engliſh prieſtes which were at the fact doing were found out, taken, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and by order of law put to death. Thus were the end of the ſaid wicked Prelates, who at their dying howers inwardly mourned, and greeuouſly lamented their miſſpent lyues, and their ill diſguyſed manners in the religion which they profeſſed before God; whoſe ſoules were drawned in the lake of couetouſnes &amp; extortion, in pride, letcherie, and
<pb facs="tcp:6036:41"/>ambition: which Prieſtes were the rather put to death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the common ſort of people dayly complayned of their wicked conuerſations, then their wilfull practiſes at faire <hi>Siluias</hi> Tombe.</p>
               <p>Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> to throw him ſelfe into the fauour of the vulgar ſort, as well to diſguiſe his owne leawd life, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the peoples murmurations, he made a reſolute deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, vtterly to diſpleaſe the religious Prelates: all which nothing preuayled to couer his wickednes, or make him the better liked amongſt the ruder people, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alwayes loatheth and miſlyketh ſtrange &amp; vnnaturall gouernments: yet this was the Phiſitians counſell, to tame and chaſtice the manners of the people; which cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed (ſayd he) except by cruelty, tirrany, iniſſgouernment, vſurpation, taxes, heauie tributes, and ſuch lyke: all other gentle meanes helped not, but rather made them more fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and in manners and conditions the more ruder.</p>
               <p>But now diſcourſe we againe of the vertuous Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> that in the middeſt of there troubles in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> had her fame and renowne made lorious in forraigne Nations: for during her abode in the <hi>Normaine</hi> Court, ſhee preferred the late Lorde high Marſhalls daughter of <hi>England</hi> to Duke <hi>Robert</hi> in marriage eſtate, who not long before had buried his Dutcheſſe, and committed her vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit, to the mighty and ſupernall maieſty of heauen. This young Lady which nowe the <hi>Normaine</hi> Duke had matched withall, by the motion and preferment of Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> was the Lorde Marſhals daughter, whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpent the beſt bloud of his heart, and yeelded his life with his famely, in the right and defence of Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therines</hi> chaſtery, (as you heard before diſcouered in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the hiſtory:) in recompence wherof the Queene thus preferred and aduanced his onely child and daughter,
<pb facs="tcp:6036:42"/>being of long time vnder her tuition educated, &amp; in hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner inſtructed.</p>
               <p>But now by the appointment of the immortal powers of heauen, Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> to the accompliſhment of al the tragicall calamities that long had oppreſſed her country <hi>England,</hi> whoſe happines ſhe inwardly in hart moſt entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loued, &amp; long ſighed after, with the ayde of the <hi>Normaine</hi> Duke and other Princes of Chriſtendome, which tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected her vertues, ſhee returned with great admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, praiſe, and renowne from her baniſhment: who being placed in a Coach of pure gold, drawne with foure milke white Palfries, with a rich imperiall Diadem vppon her head, a Septer of bright ſiluer in her hande, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gorgeous ornaments which moſt gloriouſly adorned bit princely perſon: in which ſumptuous maner ſhee ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon the coaſt of her natiue Country from whence ſhee was vniuſtly baniſhed: whereon, being no ſooner come on land, but there met her ſuch multitudes of diſtreſſed Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people that the pleaſant paſtures where ſhe trauailed ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ouerſpread, who entertained her with exceeding ioy (ſaying aloude with a generall voice) Oh happy is the hower, and bleſſed is the day that our renowned Queene is returned from baniſhment: the gods preſerue and bliſſe hir with euerlaſting peace, and ſend her long to raigne and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne vs with ioy and great tranquility, in more admired glorie then did euer Queene in this happy Iland. Theſe, and ſuch like ſpeeches was ſpoken both of young and olde, not onely to her great ioy, but to the excreding comfort of all the forraine Princes, her well willers.</p>
               <p>But nowe Lord <hi>Eſſricke</hi> and his chiefe Counſeller the Phyſition, perceiuing the whole Country to reuolt from their ſubiection, &amp; willingly yeelded to the wiſhed gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Queene <hi>Katherine:</hi> which vnexpected alteration
<pb facs="tcp:6036:42"/>cauſed them both to ſubmit themſelues to hir gratious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour: who remembring the death of Prince <hi>Edmund</hi> and the murdering of <hi>Siluia</hi> her deare children, and alſo what inconuenience and diſturbance by prolonging their liues might happen to the common-weale: Therfore in ſtraight execution ſhe commanded her will effectually to be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, which was, to haue Lord <hi>Eſſrick</hi> and his Councellers head preſently deſeuered from their ſhoulders: the which was not ſo ſtrictly commanded, as ſpeedely performed.</p>
               <p>The great proſperitie and wealth wherewith Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> by her returne from baniſhment, bewtified and inriched <hi>England,</hi> did ſo much reioice the dying ſpirits of the mournfull people, that they were glorified in their own deſires, and euerie one deemed their fortunes lifted from long continued miſery, to euerlaſting felicitie. But nowe the vertuous Queene, to make requital for the good Duke of <hi>Soffolkes</hi> baniſhment, and hainous iniuries beſides, in times paſt extended through the vnbrideled fury of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands wrath, much deſired his returne into <hi>England</hi> to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe his owne patrimonies, lands, and lofty dignities ſo long witholden from him: Therefore to the ſame effect ſhe ſent Embaſſadors ſpeedily into <hi>Porttingall,</hi> where ſhee heard he remained and gouerned in Princely eſtate: which knowledge was no ſooner giuen to the Duke, but with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, ſumptuous renowne, and aboundant of treaſures furniſhed on euery ſide, he haſtened into <hi>England:</hi> who by the vertuous Queene was receiued with ſurpaſſing glorie and magnificence: long had not theſe two princely perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages remained in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Court, but by the conſent of the whole Countrey, they were ioyned and matched together in the lawfull eſtate of marriage, by whoſe wiſe gouernement the lande of <hi>Egland</hi> in ſhort time, not only became populous, rich, honourable, and quiet: but reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb facs="tcp:6036:43"/>with all maner of neceſſary thinges. And finallie, Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> marrying the good Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> together with the conſent and aduice of the whole domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were crowned legetimate gouernors of <hi>England:</hi> where they inioyed iſſue and poſteritie betweene them, with long life, proſperous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, eternall honour, and euerlaſting felicitie.</p>
               <p>(<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by <hi>William White</hi> dwelling in Cow-lane. 1600.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6036:43"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
